<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian loue-letter sent particularly to K.T. a gentlewoman mis-styled a Catholicke, but generallie intended to all of the Romish religion, to labour their conuersion to the true faith of Christ Iesus. By Iohn Swynnerton, Gent</title>
            <author>Swynnerton, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120777</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855971</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855971</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21484</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21484)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1222:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian loue-letter sent particularly to K.T. a gentlewoman mis-styled a Catholicke, but generallie intended to all of the Romish religion, to labour their conuersion to the true faith of Christ Iesus. By Iohn Swynnerton, Gent</title>
                  <author>Swynnerton, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[84] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Iaggard dwelling in Barbican,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]²  B-L⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>K. T., --  gentlewoman.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21484:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21484:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CHRISTIAN <hi>LOVE-LETTER:</hi> Sent particularly to <hi>K.T.</hi> a Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>mis-styled</hi> A CATHOLICKE, <hi>but</hi> generallie intended to all of the Romiſh Religion, <hi>to labour their conuerſion to the true faith of CHRIST IESVS.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. Eſdras 3, 31.</bibl>
               <p>Are the deedes of Babylon better then they of Sion?</p>
            </q>
            <p>By Iohn Swynnerton, Gent:</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of a hand emerging from the clouds, with a snake entwined about the wrist, holding a staff surmounted by a portcullis, and sprays of foliage (McKerrow, 355)</figDesc>
               <p>PRVDENTIA</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by W. Iaggard dwelling</hi> in Barbican. 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21484:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21484:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, and Honorable: <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of Saliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie, <hi>vicount Cranborne, Baron of Eſſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> principall Secretarie to his Maieſtie, Mayſter <hi>of the court of Wardes and Liueries, Chancellor of the Vniuerſitie</hi> of Cambridge, knight of the Noble order of the Garter, <hi>and one of his Highneſſe moſt Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble priuy Councell</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable and my moſt honored Lord, albeit I haue no ſpecial place allotted mee in the building of the holy Temple of our Sauior, yet [I hope] I may be permitted to behold, with ioy of my ſoule, the riſing of thoſe beautifull wals, and now and then [out of a zealous deſire to haue the worke go forvvard] ſet my hand thereunto, though I ranke my ſelfe but amongſt the meaneſt of the labourers, thoſe <hi>3.</hi> ſcore and ten thouſand that beare burthens. I preſume <hi>I</hi> may: and haue therefore brought this little Stone, or peece of morter, or vvhatſoeuer it proue, to further that holy building. The rather, becauſe it is ſo maliciouſly withſtood by the crooked generation of <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres,</hi> who
[albeit they ſhall not preuaile, as the Apoſtle aſſureth them [for truth muſt haue that priuiledge] bend [notwithstanding] all their povver againſt it, &amp; do their vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to laie the ſame [though it be Gods owne houſe] leuell vvith the ground. vvho can be ſilent that hath tongue or pen in ſuch a cauſe? It is our maiſters owne quarrell. <hi>Canes latrant pro Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis ſuis tu non me vis</hi> [ſaith a learned Father] <hi>latrare pro chriſto?</hi> Yet what I haue written is but a letter, and that, a Loue-letter; but it is [moſt Noble Lord] <hi>A chriſtian Loue-letter,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvading al (though perticularly directed to one) of the Romiſhe religion, with mild and charitable phraſe, to a true faith in the bloud of Chriſt Iheſus. This letter I make bold [but in moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:21484:3"/>manner] to preſent vnto your Ho. Which in reſpect of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor [after the Phyloſophers rule] I will neither praiſe nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe <hi>Laudare ſe vani, vituperare ſtulti:</hi> yet thus much it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth me to make knowne, &amp; (without imputation of arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) I may report, that when I had writ this treatiſe (dreading the inſufficiencie or partiallity of mine owne iudgement) I appealed vnto two moſt reuerend and learned Diuines, for their cenſure; vvho vvhen they had peruſed it, ſent me away, my pains comen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the booke not diſcommended, nor my ſelfe any way diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; Othervviſe, it ſhould neuer haue ſelt the preſſe, at leaſt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue preſumed vpon ſo Honorable patronage: Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I confeſſe it is vnvvorthy your regard. But I hope your Hon: will deale no vvorſe vvith me then Chriſt did vvith the poore Widdovv in the Goſpell: ſhee brought her farthing, I bring as much: Ioffer all <hi>I</hi> haue, ſhe offerd no more: and, that vvhich ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a Mite a <hi>Million,</hi> vvith a free hart <hi>I</hi> caſt it into the treſurie. As a pledge therfore of my loue to the church of Chriſt, my loyaltie to my King and country, and laſtly of my moſt humble and my moſt dutifull affection vnto your Ho: (though <hi>I</hi> am vnknovvn vnto you, as for any extraordinary means <hi>I</hi> haue, <hi>I</hi> am euer likely to be] <hi>I</hi> moſt humblie beſeech your Lo: that the ſame may find your How and gratious acceptance.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Deuoted in all duty and ſeruice vnto your Hon: Iohn Svvynnerton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21484:3"/>
            <head>A CHRISTIAN <hi>Loue-Letter:</hi> Sent to a Gentlewoman, miſ-ſtiled a CATHOLICKE, <hi>to labour hir</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion to the true Catholicke faith <hi>of CHRIST IESVS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough Miſtris <hi>KATHARINE,</hi> from the houre I firſt vnderſtood how pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully you were miſcaried in matter of Religion, how erroneouſlie miſled in your manner of doing ſeruice to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; I euer held (and not ignorant of the diuine prohibition of raſh iudgment) the ſtate of your better part to be dangerous: yet hauing (more then curſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie) pervſed that worthie peece of work (as you take it) the little booke you ſent me, I conceiued a ſtronger ground for my opinion, and might diſcern methoght, more cleerlie, euen a lamentablenes in your condition; to haue your ſoule (after ſuch ſort) to be fed, or rather feaſted and not fed, or rather filled, and not feaſted: but to ſpeake moſt properly, neither fed, nor feaſted, nor filled, but flatly poiſoned with ſuch Italian drugs, with ſuch ſuperſtitious and Antichriſtian confections, as in the ſaid booke, and diuers other your irreligious <hi>Pamphlets</hi> of like ſubiect are compounded; while that
<pb facs="tcp:21484:4"/>bread of life, which onely ſhould feed, it is not hungred after, that vncorruptible <hi>Manna,</hi> wherewith onely it ought to be feaſted, is not gathered, that eternall food, which onely hath power to fill it, is not ſet by: I meane while the true wholſome receit
[indeed] is reiected, the pure and heauen and earth-out laſting worde of God, neither reade nor regarded. I haue felt my heart out of the generall loue of a chriſtian, and my more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar affection towardes you, almoſt melt into ſorrowe and compaſſion, to think how youly ſlabbering in theſe corrupted puddles of mans erronious inuentions, yet neuer the more clenſed, when you might with aſmuch eaſe, and much better welcome, enter that liueſome Bath of Gods owne founding, his ſacred ſcriptures, whoſe waters are of admirable operation, and
[by the hand of his bleſſed ſpirite] woulde be ſure to waſh, not onely your feete [as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh] but your handes and your head alſo [as Peter prayed,<note place="margin">Iob. 29, 6</note>] yea euen your ſoule likewiſe,<note place="margin">Iohn 13, 9 Pſal. 19, 7</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> affirmeth, and make you all ouer as white as ſnow in <hi>Salmon.</hi> You may not alledge, that the booke of God is loſt or caſt into a corner [as it was in the daies of <hi>Ioſias</hi>] or that his ſacred writings,<note place="margin">2 chr. 34, 14 Iere. 36, 23</note> are cut in peeces, and throwne into the fire, as they were by the handes of <hi>Iehoiachim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You cannot pleade any famine of the worde of God [which of all other inflictions, the Lord for his mercye ſake euermore auert from our nation] that ſhoulde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force you to feede ſo eagerly vpon ſuch groſſe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſome garbadge, for a greater plenty, and freer paſſage thereof, the King of heauen haue the glorye, as we haue the gaine, neuer any kingdome of the earth
[I thinke] inioyed. The truth is, neither you, nor the
<pb facs="tcp:21484:4"/>greateſt clark that euer breathd ſuperſtition vpon you, can bring a ſubſtantiall reaſon to excuſe your vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the ſcriptures, conſidering you may read them, and heare them truely read, and expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded [if you pleaſe] and that it is our ſauiours owne precept, <hi>Search the ſcriptures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 5, 39 Mar. 12, 29</note> and a concluſion of his owne framing, <hi>Erre not knowing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If an ordinarie friende ſhould counſell you to doe a thing within your power, that would be neither charga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nor trouble ſome vnto you, and withall annex vnto his aduiſe a forcible reaſon, importing ſome ſingular benefit, that ſhould redound in doing it, woulde you not with all readineſſe vndertake it, and moſt willinglie embrace his counſell? I know you would: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot chuſe but woonder, when that extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie friend of yours <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> who held you [I cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritablie include you amongſt the choſen] as precious as his owne heart blood, and whome you ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteeme more deere then your owne ſoule, ſhall offer you his owne booke to read, commaund you to read it, and withall aſſertaine you, that you goe aſtraie, and wander out of the right waie that leadeth to felicitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you want that direction, which the ſame woulde affoorde you: To ſee you notwithſtanding ſhut your eies, and eares, and all your ſences to be delighted and euen rauiſhed with ſuch harſh ſounding, and vnmelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious harmonie; ſuch abſurd, and hereticall doctrine, as this booke which I receiued from you, and other of the like ſtampe [to frequent amongeſt you] are ſtuffed with; Wherein I graunt, ſome part of Goddes worde [to countenaunce forth all the reſt] is heere and there
<pb facs="tcp:21484:5"/>inter-wouen, but that either not it ſelfe through cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt tranſlation, or at leaſt not like it ſelfe, it is ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentlie wreſted, and by miſapplication ſo pittifully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured. When I had read your booke, entituled; <hi>A quartern of reaſons of catholicke Religion, with as manie briefe reaſons of refuſall, collected and compoſed by T. Hill, Doctor of Diuinity,</hi> and hadde weighed the ſubiect, the ſtile, and the method, I adiudged the anſwering of it to be a matter of no great difficultie, and [methought] no taske of impoſſibilitie for my ſelfe: though [as you know] no profeſſed Diuine, no noted ſtudent, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed not worthie the name of a Scholler; Howſoeuer, yet I vndertook it, till in my return fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you out of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſhire, at the Stationers in Worſter I light vpon a booke bearing this title, <hi>A quartern of reaſons compoſed by D. Hill vnquartered and proued a quartern of follies, by Francis Dillingham Batcheler of Diuinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon ſeeing the Doctor ſo ſubſtantiallie dealt with by M. <hi>Dillingham,</hi> a degree behind him one waie, though manie degrees before him another waie, and to haue receiued from him a more ſufficient anſwer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my pouertie could haue affoorded, I willing lie ſurcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſo let fall my former reſolution: yet being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſaile, ſeeing the wind faire, and feeling my ſelfe to brook pretilie wel the Ocean <hi>I</hi> was entred into, <hi>I</hi> thoght to make a voyage of it [though a contrarie waie] before I returned; <hi>I</hi> meane, hauing taken pen in hand, to haue anſwered [in my vnlearned faſhion, and therefore the more ſuteable] the foreſaide Treatiſe, and perceiuing my ſelfe ſo happilie preuented, <hi>I</hi> determined notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to write ſomething vnto you, that ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerne you, and whereby [if God were ſo pleaſed] that
<pb facs="tcp:21484:5"/>more then <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſſe wherwith yourſoule is ſo benighted, might in a timely houre bee expelled.</p>
            <p>For two chiefe reaſons haue <hi>I</hi> made religion the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of this my letter; the firſt, for that [there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnder the glory of God] that ſo highlie impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth you, as the good eſtate of your ſoule, which depen deth vpon the religion you profeſſe in the daies of this your pilgrimage vpon earth. The other reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the difference of your religion &amp; mine [our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie opinion therein] hath bin the principall impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that interrupted our loues proceeding, &amp; brake the marriage betwixt vs, which the worlde ſo long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and we [but for that] mutually deſired. For as <hi>I,</hi> vpon ſure ground was euer reſolued one way, ſo you [though without ground] were as reſolut another way; and ſtill would intimate your deſire of my reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to your Catholicke Religion (as you call it.] In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed for a Gentlewoman that is a catholike, to ponder aforehand that irreligion, though it cannot lawfullie breake that indiſſoluble band, yet ought to be helde of ſufficient force to reſtraine [at firſt] the making there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is a prudent conſideration.</p>
            <p>For her to weigh with her ſelfe that this word <hi>coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium,</hi> or wedlocke, importeth a vniting of two mindes and that if ſhe match with one contrarily affected in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the only true tempred ſtuffe that ſoldreth harts togither, they, can neuer rightly accord, becauſe they cannot agree in loue, that diſagree in faith. This is like wiſe an ingenious and religious caution.</p>
            <p>And then if ſhe in true zeale and vpon the forſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, conuert that hereticke
[whom ſhe loueth] to the profeſſion of the catholike faith, before ſhe dain
<pb facs="tcp:21484:6"/>him the title of her husband, Queſtionleſſe ſhe doth a worke that pleaſeth God, profiteth his church, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth matter of reioycing to the Angels of heauen. But ſtandeth the cauſe thus betwixt vs two, I dare ſweare [for I had rather think you any thing then a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembler] you thinke it doth: you thinke your elfe a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke, and mean heretick; you thinke the cuſtome of our young gentlewomen of your old religion, in tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their husbands hearts, to the imbracing of their opinions, a laudable cuſtome; and ought by you like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as ſtrictlie to be obſerued: But alaſſe that ſuch blindneſſe [were it otherwiſe, pleaſing to our great God, whoſe wiſedome beſt knoweth what is good for his Church] ſhould get ſuch poſſeſſion of your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and Ignorance, ſo ouercloude your iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to make you deeme your ſelfe to be otherwiſe then you are, and others to be euen as the vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt of your conſtructions can make them. Alaſſe I ſaie, vnder the foreſaid reſeruation, that it ſhould be ſo, howbeit I maruaile not, that it is ſo, ſince it hath bin proper to the heriticks of old, preiudicatlie, to arrogate vnto themſelues that acceptable appellation of catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and to intitle the catholiks indeed, by this odious attribute of hereticks. But now (methinks) you begin to diſtaſt my phraſe, becauſe it begins to deale round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with you, in retorting (thoughe couertlie) the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick thus vpon you: be patient a while, and becauſe no man that iudgeth himſelfe ſound is eaſilie wonne to accept the Phiſitians helpe, hovv full of vertue ſoeuer the Medicine be, which is tendred him: giue me leaue I praie you, firſt to make you knovv your ſelfe to be imperfected, &amp; then I doubt not, but the receipt,
<pb facs="tcp:21484:6"/>which the ſmall meaſure of my skill ſhal compound, for the expelling of your infirmitie, will not onely be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto your taſt, but powerfull [through his working that giueth power to euery good work] for your reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery. It hath bin held a profitable method, in the diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of any vice to anotamize that vertue which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlie the oppoſite; for the hard fauored gentlewoman is neuer ſo diſaduantaged, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe goes hand in hand with her beutiful neighbor; each thing [indeed] being beſt deciphered by his contrarie. I will therefore
[the queſtion being which of vs is the catholicks] firſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mine own faith, which you hold to be no better then hereſie, &amp; the verie contrarie vnto yours; that thereby the beutie of your profeſſion, if mine be ſo deformed, may the more bee admired, or rather [as I hope] and [if iudiciall eies impartially diſcerne berwixt vs aſſure my ſelfe] that the impuritie, and blemiſhes thereof, by ſuch oppoſition of mine, ſo ſubſtantially warrantable may the ſooner be reuealed, and by yourſelfe whom it ſo neerelie concernes the better diſcerned: and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I begin with diſcloſing the ſubſtance of mine owne profeſſion, becauſe we are bound to ſind the true faith of chriſt in our ſelues, before we examine the want therof in others, and ought readilie to giue a reckoning of the ſame, if either authority
[that is ſufficient] in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne, or cauſes [that are ſubſtantial] as in this caſe ſhal induce vs therunto.</p>
            <p>MY religion [vnderſtand me I praie you] <hi>Is the true worſhip of the euerliuing God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Sect.</note> I know it is the true worſhip of God becauſe it is that manner and forme of worſhip, which is agreeable to his bleſſed wil; I know it is agreeable to his wil, becauſe it is framed acording to
<pb facs="tcp:21484:7"/>the preſcription of his holy word: And <hi>I</hi> know it to be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med according to his word, becauſe <hi>I</hi> learne the ſame out of his owne booke, which containeth nothing but his word; deliuered firſt by his owne voice to our fore fathers, after indighted by his owne al-ſufficient wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, penned downe by his owne choſen ſeruants the prophets and Apoſtles, ſealed and confirmed with the precious bloud of his owne deere ſonne, and from age to age, through perſecution, through captiuitie, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the moſt powerfull occurrents that euer Sathan deuiſed, for impugning the ſame, by his owne woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull prouidence ſo mercifully preſerued, to be food for the ſoules, and direction for the liues of his elect here on earth, while the world endureth, which booke we therefore intitle the ſacred ſcriptures, &amp; common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Bible: ſo that my Religion is, <hi>a worſhipping of god after his owne will, reuealed by his owne word comprized in his owne booke:</hi> and therfore as <hi>I</hi> firſt ſaid, <hi>a true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the euerliuing God.</hi> And, is it not [iudge you] the wiſeſt courſe we can take for the vnderſtanding the wil of our God, without which we are no better then the beaſts that periſh, and which neceſſarilie wee muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto before we can do it, as we muſt doe it; before we receiue that which you call the wages of wel-doing. To read diligentlie this book, to ſearch reuerently theſe ſcriptures, and to haue continuall recourſe vnto this word, which may be called the truſty Embaſſador that faithfullie deliuereth the reuealed councels of God, the holy mouth that truely vttereth the oracles of his bleſſed ſanctuarie, which is the word of life, the worde of truth, as true as himſelfe, his owne word, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beſt reuealer of his will, and moſt abſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriber
<pb facs="tcp:21484:7"/>of that platforme, after which hee delighteth to be worſhipped.</p>
            <p>I will not by way of inference as I go along, roue at any marks of your profeſſion, til I haue in ſom perfecter ſort meaſured out mine owne, elſe could I [me thinks] with an arrow drawne out of this quyuer, pierce euen the quickeſt vaine of thoſe vnwarranted <hi>Decretals,</hi> and humaine <hi>Traditions</hi> of yours. But let your thoughtes a while be beſtowed in conſideration of what I ſay touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mine owne religion, which earſt I deſined to be, <hi>The true worſhipe of the euerliuing God.</hi> Wherein leaſt you ſhould miſtake, in thinking I deale <hi>Pharaſaically,</hi> or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute perfection of impoſſibility vnto my ſelfe, who being but fleſh, am therefore full of ſinne, and thereby diſabled for that righteous cariage, and the perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of thoſe holy offices, which properly belong to the ſeruice of him, who is all righteouſneſſe, and true holines it ſelfe: conceiue I pray you, how I vnderſtand my ſelfe, and deſire to be vnderſtood therein. I confeſſe that all men are ſinners, and my ſelfe as ſinfull as any man, I might ſaie more ſinful, for I muſt iudge my ſelfe ſeuerely, and of others charitably: beſides, <hi>I knowe mine owne wickedneſſe, and my ſinne is euer before me.</hi> The Angels of heauen, that excell in ſtrength may keep (o happy, happie are they that while) the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord, but the inhabitants of the earth, that are compoſed of weakeneſſe, doe nothing but breake them; In a word, I am one of <hi>Adams</hi> crooked brats, <hi>My workes are impure, and all my righteouſneſſe as a polluted cloute.</hi> So that to doe true worſhip to that <hi>Euerliuing God</hi> (as I profeſſed) of my ſelfe, I am not able, for a ſinfull lumpe of fleſhe, I finde it impoſſible. <hi>Who am I</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21484:8"/>(ſaid <hi>Moyſes</hi> in a timerous diſtruſt of his owne abilitie,)<note place="margin">Exod. 3, xi</note> that I ſhold go vnto <hi>Pharo.</hi> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what am I, maie I better expoſtulate from the certaine knowledge of my diſabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, to worſhip the <hi>Euarlaſting God?</hi> What am I, that am a thouſand times inſerior to that <hi>Moſes,</hi> to worſhip him truelie, who is ten thouſand, nay innumerable and vnimaginarie millions of degrees ſuperior to that <hi>Pharo.</hi> But the ſame God, who [in reſpect of his owne deſert, being the perfection of all thinges, and all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection before thinges had being] requireth ſuch exact ſeruice from me, knowes whereof I am made, for I am, <hi>a worke of his owne handes,</hi> and remembreth that, <hi>I am but duſt</hi> the ſubſtance of my forefathers, vnskilfull how [for I am no better then <hi>a beaſt in my owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> and vnapt if I were skillfull, ſo to ſerue him, <hi>My hearte by nature being continually ſo miſdiſpoſed.</hi> And out of the great ſtorehouſe therefore of his vnualua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble compaſſion, hath he ſent me a full ſupplie to all my deſects, and plainelie directed me how to adreſſe my ſelfe for the manner of ſeruice, which muſt purchaſe his acceptation: for as he gaue encouragement to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and taught him with his owne word what to ſaie vnto, and howe to carrie himſelfe before <hi>Pharo.</hi> It hath pleaſed him in like ſort to imbolden mee in my greateſt ſeare, and by the perfect rule of the ſame powerfull word, to inſtruct me after what ſorte to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before him, and how to demeane my ſelfe in the preſence of his Maieſtie, his ſacred word [I ſaie ſtill] the ſpirit of truth expounding the ſame vnto me, is my inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Hence I learne [which is the leſſon that all chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſhould be perfect in] the knowledge of Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:21484:8"/>chriſt, and him crucified, to know him to be perfect God and perfect Man, my maker, my ſauiour, my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator. My maker as he is God, my Sauiour and media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, as he is God and man: this is all I deſire to knowe, and may be wel enough, for that learned Apoſtle of his, notwithſtanding his miraculous conuerſion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant inſpiration, and heauenly viſion, [by his own teſtimonie, knew no more, as he needed not, the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine thereof being [indeede] the verie ſumme, and ſcope of the whole ſcriptures. This knowledge whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hath, though he knowe nothing elſe, knoweth all thinges: as who ſo wanteth the ſame, though hee knowe all thinges elſe, maye bee ſaide to knovve no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>This is that chriſtall ſountain from whence the pure Waters of life do flovv, and they that drinke ſoundlie thereof ſhall neuer thirſt. This is that fixed <hi>Helice</hi> which if we truelie obſerue, pointeth out our land of promiſe, and directeth vs the right waie thither; Nay, this is the waie it ſelfe that leades vs vnto truth; and the truth it ſelfe that leades vnto life; and the life it ſelfe that vve ſo long after, euen eternall ſelicitie, <hi>I am the way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 14, 6.</note> 
               <hi>the truth and the life:</hi> Novv, from this knowledge of my ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior, I learn to renounce my ſelfe and relie vpon him, to caſt off mine own beggerlie rags patched together with abhomination, and by the hand of faith to put on his princely robe, the glorious robe of his righteouſnes. In this attire I appeare before my god, &amp; become accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his preſence, for this garment he frely giueth me, and as freely teacheth me how to weare it: I meane this righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, which is the true conſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie with the law of GOD, and an abſolute ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling
<pb facs="tcp:21484:9"/>thereof: God, out of his meere grace and mercy impureth vnto me, and withall woo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>keth in me faith, whereby I apply the ſame vnto my ſelfe, ſo that in this ſence, I may preſume to ſay the righteouſnes of Chriſt is mine, and that therein I ſerue my God truely, as he that laboured ſo much euen to anotamize the worke of iuſtification, hath for an eternall <hi>Maxime</hi> ſet downe, that <hi>Christ is made vnto vs righteouſnes, wiſedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 cor. 1, 30</note> 
               <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, and redemption,</hi> and elſe where, <hi>That in him we are compleat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2, 10</note> The fraile wit of man hath deuiſed a law, whereby an act doue by one is remitted from him that did it, to him that gaue conſent and commiſſion for the doing of it. But the vnſearchable wiſedome of our God, from the deepe reach of his mercy, and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, without ſo much as our knowledge (for he knew vs from euerlaſting, and before the foundation of the worlde, contriued this meanes for our deliuery]hath more then admirably conueyed vnto vs the memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble act of Chriſtes humiliation and ſatisfaction, and by his imputation, and our aprehenſion (which is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe his guifte) freelye made it ours. The worke it ſelfe which is <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> not altred by the exchange of the ſubiect, but onely inattribute. It being <hi>I egall in Christ,</hi> in vs <hi>Euangelicall:</hi> If then the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt thus be made ours, if his obedience and ſatisfaction be thus freely beſtowed vppon vs: What ſhould hinder vs (it may be meruailed) from affording due entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſo vnſpeakeable a benefit, and that we make not true vſe of ſo great aduantage. Is not this the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectableſt food that euer any hungry ſtomacke longed after? Is it not the ſofteſt couch that the wearied ſoule can find to repoſe vpon? Queſtionleſſe it is, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:21484:9"/>whoſoeuer reſolueth to fare well, ſhoulde frame himſelfe to this diet, and he that loueth to lie ſoft, muſt become his owne Harbinger, and make ſure in time to take vp this lodging: For this is the food of eternall life, this is the bed of euerlaſting reſt. <hi>Peter</hi> not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but being then, (and not only then) out of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Element [for he knew not what he ſaid] brake with chriſt about building of <hi>tabernacles on the mount Thabar.</hi> But hee that vppon this foundation which is chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhall aduiſedly erect the fortreſſe of his hope, and Tabernacle of his felicity, may be truely ſaid to be his owne man, though ſcarcely as the apprehenſion of men goeth now a daies, and that he is in the right, For he knowes what he doth, and that his building, though all thoſe wordely, fleſhly, and diuelliſh aduerſaries, combino in oppugnation, can neuer be ſubuerted. In more propper ſence therefore then <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake it, I may boldely ſay, <hi>Heere is good being,</hi> good for the King, good for the Begger, good for all, heere is good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed, and heere am I conſtantly reſolued, let ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo many millions of miſbeleeuers reſt vppon what other rotten dependance they liſt, to ſet downe my reſt for euer.</p>
            <p>This ſtay I know to be ſure and neuer ſhrincking: this ſupportation I am ſure is ſtrong and neuer ſhaketh. This, this is our ſoules moſt firme, and neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>failing anchorage: yea this righteouſnes of our ſweete, and louing ſauiour, is not onely a ſure ſtrong and neuer failing foundation, but it is the onely ſure ſtronge and neuer failing foundation, whereupon we muſt reſolue to build all our happines for euer, if euer we reſolue to
<pb facs="tcp:21484:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21484:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21484:11"/>for to relie vpon ought beſides, that the earth, or the heauens themſelues can afford, in the great and weightie cauſe of our iuſtification, is to truſt vnto that which ſhall neuer ſtedde vs, and moſt vndoubtedlie to become moſt vnhappie. Now, this righteouſneſſe of our mercifull redeemer, ſo aduantageable to all thoſe that conſtantly depend thereuppon, I conſider in his perfect obeying to the law of God, which we had tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, and coulde neuer of our ſelues haue fulfilled, and his painefull vndergoing the puniſhment pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſuch our tranſgreſſions, euen the wrath of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which was incenſed, &amp; by no ſatisfaction of man, or Angel could euer haue bin appeaſed. O ſweet, vnef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable and incomprehenſible mercie of our God, who out of his owne boſome hath diſtilled a balme to cure all our wounds, though neuer ſo mortall, and albeit ſo deſeruedlie receiued in the traiterous breach of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ordinaunces, and not ſpared euen his owne heart bloud, to waſh awaie our vncleanneſſe, and to purge vs that were his enemies, from all our corruption. The meanes that conueieth vnto us this mercie of God the father in this merite of God the ſonne, is [as I former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched] a liuelie iuſtifieng faith, begotten in our harts by God the Holi-ghoſt, who muſt needes be thefficient cauſe of the ſaid Faith, as the true knowledge and truſt in Chriſt is the formall, the goſpell the inſtrumentall, and the finall gods glorie. By which faith, it being <hi>The ground of thinges which are hoped for,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 11, 1</note> 
               <hi>and the euidence of things which are not ſeene,</hi> or a ſtedfaſt ſupernaturall knowledge and firme apprehenſion of Gods kindnes in <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> towards vs. Many celeſtiall indowmentes and good workes are kindled in the mind and hart, and
<pb facs="tcp:21484:11"/>flame forth of the life and conuerſation of euerie true beleeuer; as repentance, hope, loue, inuocation, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, iuſtification, adoption, patience, conſolation, mortification, peace of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ioy in the holighoſt, and regeneration with the fruits therof: All of them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither with diuers other ſuch like heauenlie infuſed qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, though not diſtinguiſhable in time but in nature, though eſſentially being Gods gifts, and immediatelie proceeding from his grace, yet properlie either begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, wrought or apprehended by the ſaide Faith, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in vs a cauſe, &amp; they the neceſſarie effects, the root, and they the inſeperable braunches: So that when I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme my religion to be, <hi>The true ſeruice of God</hi> and that ſeruice to be performed truelie by vs, in the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Chriſt, I do not herein exclude our workes as impertinent or vnneceſſarie thereunto, or deny but that good workes are Gods ſeruices, and that therein it pleaſeth him to be glorified: But becauſe our workes when they are at the beſt are of themſelues imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and when they finde the happieſt paſſage, not for themſelues, but in and for Chriſts righteouſnes are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, I iudge it a more proper ſpeech to ſay, that in the righteouſnes of Chriſt which is abſolutely perfect, which is freely beſtowed vpon vs, and really made ours by faith, and from which as from the fountaine of all Gods graces, all our owne good workes are properlie ſaide to ſpring, that therein we ſerue God truely [it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it ſelf as it wel deſerueth merritorious, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our poor endeuours, which of themſelues deſerue nothing, moſt gratiouſly to be regarded.</p>
            <p>Indeede it is all in all vnto vs, reconciling vs to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of our God, and inablinge vs to doe that which
<pb facs="tcp:21484:12"/>is acceptable both before God and man: for where this righteouſneſſe is faithfully receiued; This righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, through which only we enioy all the bleſſings of the earth, by which onely (as I ſaid) our beſt deedes muſt purchaſe acceptation, and for which only we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently hope, at the laſt daie to be ſaued: where I ſaie this righteouſneſſe is truely apprehended by faith, by vertue of the ſame the heart, and all the powers of the whole man, are inſtantly preſt (ſo much as in him lies) for al godly deſigns, and eagerly bent (ſo far as by grace he is inabled) to the execution of any religious office, that may tend to the ſeruice of his Lord and ſauiour, and to the manifeſtation of his obedience, loue, and thankefulneſſe to his maieſtie, for ſuch his vnſpeakable mercy towardes him: for looke how proper light is to the ſunne or heate to fire, ſo proper, and ſo inſeparable are good workes vnto that faithe which is ſo ſurely founded vpon the mercie of God, in this righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> No I am ſo far from renouncing or diſclaiming from good works, that I will acompany any true, or ſtiled catholick, proteſtant or papiſt in the world, in commendation, eſtimation, and approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, till they come to be ſo intollerably prized, as to be ſet in the roome of chriſtes righteouſneſſe, to fulfill the eternall law of God, which was Chriſts office, to be held meritorious of ſaluation, which is the due of chriſts obedience; and conſequently to be made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable with Gods iuſtice, which is onely proper to chriſts righteouſneſſe; In this degree of magnifieng them I hold it ſecurity to leaue them, acknoledging my pouerty one waie, [acording to that rate] not able to reach them: and knowing my riches another way (after
<pb facs="tcp:21484:12"/>ſuch a reckoning not to ſtand in neede of them, for <hi>We are poore in our ſelues but rich in Chriſt,</hi> I confeſſe that to glorifie God by doing good workes, is a principall end both of our election, creation, redemption, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: I confeſſe that workes are neceſſary, for great and waightie reſpects, as beſides the honnouring of God, which is the chiefe end of all, and to be preferred before any reſpect whatſoeuer, to manifeſt our faith, to credit our vocation, to expreſſe our thankefulneſſe, to benefite our neighbour, and to acertaine vs, that wee are in the right waie, that leadeth to euerlaſting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; yea ſo farre fourth neceſſarie, that without them, I meane without the workes of the ſecond, or at leaſt of the firſt Table, we ſhall neuer attain vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Howbeit, I dare not thence conclude, that thoſe workes are the cauſe of our ſaluation, but the effects of the cauſe, which is faith in the righteouſneſſe of chriſt.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe that all our good workes ſhal be rewarded euen to a cup of cold Water, yet will not thereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, that ſuch reward is extended for the merit either of the perſon that doth the worke, or of the worke how wel done ſoeuer, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the meere bounty of our god, who dealeth with vs (in all things) better then (of our ſelues) we deſerue; and for manifeſtation of his truth, who hath gaged his word to that effect, and will euer be as good as his promiſe. In a worde I approue good workes, I honour the doers of them, and admire that grace which by faith enableth men to do them: but ſtil vnderſtand them to be the fruites and conſequents of faith, and in vs to receiue their life and being from the ſame; for I cannot thinke that repentance or charity themſelues, though both of them ſteed vs ſo much in
<pb facs="tcp:21484:13"/>this world, &amp; the one of them ſtay with vs in the world to come, are ſent by the bleſſed ſpirit, into the heartes or mindes of the faithfull, till faith formerly planted there by the ſame ſpirit, be ready to receiue them. For I know they are diuine vertues, and no ſinnes: Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it had they being before faith, I durſt not thinke them ſo,<note place="margin">Ro, 14, 23</note> becauſe I am commaunded to hold the neceſſity of this conſequent <hi>whatſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne,</hi> to be inuincible. A legall contrition [indeede] and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine effection may goe before, but when that contrition becommeth true repentance, and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is refined into perfect charity: Queſtionleſſe, it is faith, it being the receiuer of the ſpirit and purifier of the hart, by which vnder God is wrought that happy and heauenly metamorphoſis.</p>
            <p>BVt to wade no deeper in this bottomleſſe Ocean, where the pilate himſelfe if he take not good heed, may quickly ſinck ouer head and eares,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Sect.</note> ſo infinite are the miſteries of our redemption, and ſo many degrees more then infinite the mercies of God in our redemer: And becauſe I ſtand in feare, leaſt for the difficulty, you conceite not, or for the ſtrangenes therof affect not this deſcription, which I haue already made of my Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I will after a plainer ſort for your vnderſtanding, and in a faſhion more ſutable for our liking, draw forth in a word or two that pattern which in the profeſſion of my faith and action of my life, till the daies of my pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gramage, in this vaile of affliction bee determined, I am reſolued by the ayde of the bleſſed ſpirit preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to follow; and whence as touching the diſcharge of my duty both towardes God, and man, I fetch my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.
<pb facs="tcp:21484:13"/>I formerly implyed, that this patterne was the written word, and ſo I doe ſtill for <hi>the worde of God is a Lanthorne vnto our feete, and a light vnto our pathes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa, 119</note> a Lanthorne to keepe our feete from falling, in the race that we are to runne for ſo greate a Wager, and a light to make our pathes though they be narrow, and otherwiſe impoſſible to be hit, yet plain &amp; paſſable vnto vs: but an <hi>Epitomy</hi> onely of this word I wil now propoſe vnto you, which conſiſteth of the creede, the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and the lords praier; the creed indited by the holy ghoſt, and (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> probability) penned by the apoſtles, howſoeuer yet compoſed of their doctrine, &amp; therfore not vnworthily called their creed The commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments indited [and penned to for ought we knowe by god himſelfe] and deliuered to his choſen ſeruant <hi>Moſes</hi> on the Mount <hi>Synay:</hi> and the Lords prayer indicted, by chriſt our ſauior, and afterwards penned down, by thoſe heauenly inſpired actuaries of his, the holy Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts; the creed comprizing the ſubſtance of the goſpel, which is a ioyfull meſſage of ſaluation, beſtowed vpon vs vnder a condition of faithfull beleeuing: The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the ſum of the law, which is an aſſurance of eternal life vnto vs, but vnder a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a harder nature, namely the exact performance of our dutye towardes God, and our neighbour, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in theſe commaundementes; And the Lordes prayer contayning an abſolute Method of inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or a perfect rule how to offer the ſacryfice of prayſe and praier vnto our God, wherewith he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe to be honored, and wherin our ſeruice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his maieſty
[eſpecially fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our inward man] is moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually performed the creed, which is our law of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing.
<pb facs="tcp:21484:14"/>The commaundements which are our lawes of liuing, and the Lords prayer which is our law of praiſing and praying, and long ſince for the dignity of it intituled e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Law likewiſe of liuing, and beleeuing: Now, the creed, the commaundements, and the Lords pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, being thus in effect, a compendious breuiarie of the whole Bible, which containeth the ſacred worde of the euerliuing God, whereby his bleſſed will, for our maner of ſeruing him is manifeſtly reuealed vnto vs; and the definition of my religion being <hi>a true ſeruice of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing God, according to his will reuealed in his worde,</hi> I am warranted (not anye way impugning the ſame) to affirm, that my religion is, to beleeue according to the creed, to liue according to the commaundements, and to inuocate the name of God according to the Lordes praier. Howbeit, I vnderſtand not heere this word (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording) in ſence of abſolute coroſpondence, with the creede, the commaundements and the Lordes prayer; But vnder this humble and neceſſary reſeruation, namely that I beleeue according to the creede, as ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly, and aſſuredly, that I liue according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, as vprightly and conformably, and that I inuocate the name of God, according to the Lordes prayer as zealouſly and effectually, as the meaſure of faith, grace, and the ſpirit do enable me: For theſe are al Gods giftes, and he freely beſtoweth them vppon his needy followers, in proportion that is beſt pleaſing to his vnchaungeable will, and moſt agreeable to his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable wiſedome: For I dare not thinke better of my ſelfe in the ability of beleeuing, liuing and praying, then my betters haue formerly done of themſelues: [O that I were ſo gratiouſly qualified, wherby I might iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:21484:14"/>be occaſioned to thinke ſo wel] my betters, I meane the beſt of Gods ſeruants, ſome of them hauing cryed vnto the Lord for helpe to their vnbeleefe, and to haue theyr fayth increaſed: Some hauing agnized that the godlyeſt ſeuen times a day, ſhew what houſe they are come of, whoſe loynes they proceed from, that <hi>Adam</hi> the ringleader of man-ſinners, was their anceſtor: and ſome auerring that we of our ſelues know not, what to praye as wee ought, and therefore [to helpe vs out] that the ſpirit it ſelfe maketh requeſt for vs with ſighes that cannot be expreſſed. Wherefore [as in effect I ſaide before] I beleeue as the meaſure of faith doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten me acording to the creed: I liue as the meaſure of grace doth enable me, according to the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements: and I pray as the meaſure of the ſpirit doeth informe me, according to the Lordes prayer. Thus I beleeue, thus I liue, thus I pray, this is my religion, and [as I take it] <hi>The true ſeruice of the euerliuing God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will reuealed in his word.</hi> Nowe, hauing [as I promiſed] after that little glimpſe of vnderſtanding, by the mercy of my God, reſerued in me, giuen you a view of my profeſſion, which through the ſubtilitie of Sathan, playing vpon your ſimplicity, you are ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly borne in hand, is ſo erronious, abſurd, and Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; I would gladly know wherein ſuch hereſie, abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie or error can be found: but it was my promiſe, and is ſtill my purpoſe [if God, that diſpoſeth of all thinges howſoeuer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> purpoſeth be pleaſed therwith] to make you ſee the vnſeemelines of your owne miſhapen opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and to feele the daungerouſneſſe of your owne ſouls diſeaſe, by vnderſtanding the errour, abſurditie, and hereſie of your owne religion. Which I knowe not
<pb facs="tcp:21484:15"/>how better or in plainer ſort to perform, then by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before your view the doctrin of your Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> church, in oppoſition to the doctrin of our church of England, touching theſe principall heads of a chriſtians profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which I haue already, [though briefly, and but in part] runne ouer, that ſo comparing the one with the other, and trying them both by the touchſtone, that diſcouereth truth from falſhood, you may more iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially deſcerne the currant from the counterfeit, and more powerfully be induced (hauing once found ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable a Iewell) to long after the ful fruition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which [although you ſell all you haue to gaine it] wil not prooue deere vnto you, for it wil make you rich vnto eternall ſaluation.</p>
            <p>AND firſt againſt my religion,<note place="margin">4. Sect.</note> which I defined, and proued to be <hi>The true ſeruice of the euerliuing God, according to his wil reuealed in his word,</hi> I muſt be ſo bold with yours, as to call it, <hi>a forged ſeruice of God according to the will of man, reuealed in traditians, decretals, and counſels:</hi> I may tearme it, <hi>a forged ſeruice of God,</hi> becauſe it is according to the will of man only, and not of God; and I dare ſay, it is according to the will of man onely, becauſe it is onely reuealed in theſe <hi>Traditions,</hi> meerely humaine, vnwarrantable <hi>Decretals,</hi> and Counſels not lawfully called: and are you not in a hard caſe already, euen vppon this entraunce into conſideratior. of your religion? Doe you not thinke it a miſerable condition, whereunto with their plauſible perſwaſions, they whom you deeme your ghoſtly fathers, [but by the Holighoſt himſelfe, are deſcribed by <hi>creeping into houſes and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding captiue ſilly Women,</hi> ſuch as your ſelf] haue done their beſt to tie you? Is it not [and be your own iudge] a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous caſe, and a condition moſt diſaduantagable ſo to be traduced, to faſten your ſoules dependance vpon
<pb facs="tcp:21484:15"/>a courſe of ſeruing God, which neither by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, nor Chriſt Ieſus his ſonne, nor by his faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants the prophets, or Apoſtles, was euer commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; no nor by the general conſent of the fathers of the primitiue church for 5. C. years at leaſt after <hi>Chriſts</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, euer preſcribed, or practiſed. For your ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration &amp; inuocation of Sa. your praiers for the ſouls of your friends departed, your ſuperſtitious pilgrimages, your communion vnder one kind only, your calling vp on God for you know not what, in a tongue you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not, your ſacrifice of the maſſe, your meriting by your works, and diuers other ſuch like groſſe &amp; abſurd opinions, wherupon your religion is compoſed, as they can find no ſubſtantiall warrant, in the ſacred canonical ſcriptures, which are Gods pure truth, and containe all things neceſſary for our ſaluation. So had they not their birth immediately vpon the Apoſtles death, but ſome of them ſprang vp two hundred, ſome three hundred, ſome fiue hundred years after, ſome ſooner, ſome later, and were not al til within this very age, euen the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of men now liuing, by your ſelus conſented vnto, nor abſolutely by your owne vſurped authority concluded vpon. Hence may you eaſily gather [your religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither ſufficiently waranted by authority of Gods word, nor generally approued by the ancient fathers of the church] how woorthily or vnworthily you ſtile the ſame with ſuch confidence, the old and catholicke reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: I cannot go on with particular examination of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery part of your profeſſion, your patience, and my lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, being I fear proportionable wil not permit me, but do beg your atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion to the conſideration of one prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal point of doctrine, generally taught by your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt clarks, &amp; as generally beleeued euen to the ſimpleſt
<pb facs="tcp:21484:16"/>amongſt you, whoſe ſtomackes indeed are the beſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſters of ſuch miſdiet becauſe <hi>at the hands of ignorance, errour euer findeth her ſecureſt entertainment,</hi> I former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, in diſcourſe of our Religion affirmed, that our whole dependance for our ſaluation was vpon the free mercy of God through chriſt Ieſus: And the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of chriſt without any worke or merit of our owne applyed truely by faith, was before God our on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iuſtification: contrary to this doctrin, you are taught and do beleeue that you ſhall be ſaued by your workes, or at leaſt that your workes muſt concur, and ſtand vp with faith in the act of your iuſtification before God. Now to make you ſee and acknowledge the abſurdity and preiudice of this opinion: firſt you ſhall heare what the Apoſtle himſelfe inſpired with the holy ſpirit, and the fathers of the church hauing the ſame diuine ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter, though inſtructed in farre different meaſure, haue thought and deliuered touching the ſame; and then ſom principal inconueniences that neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that doctrine, pregnant and aparant enough [I hope] vtterly to deterre you from euer lending a liſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eare againe thereunto.<note place="margin">Titus. 3, 5</note> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> that writ more tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the manner of our iuſtification then all the reſt of the Apoſtles, to make his Scholler <hi>Titus,</hi> and others by him to abandon all hope of being ſaued by their works, telleth him plainely, <hi>We are ſaued not by workes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe which we haue done, but acording to his mercy he ſaued vs:</hi> Heere he excludeth workes, though they be works of righteouſnes, though they be our beſt works, and aſcribeth all the matter of our ſaluation meerely to the mercy of God through Ieſus chriſt; I am ſure, there is no worke that you or the holieſt of your church
<pb facs="tcp:21484:16"/>whatſoeuer can do, that is a better worke more merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, a worke of purer righteouſneſſe then the workes of <hi>Paule</hi> were. No, they hold in no compariſon with his, for his workes (as yours doe not) ſprang from a liuely faith, which made them ſo good as they were, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, you ſee he vtterly renounceth them all how good ſoeuer, and dare you in any ſort reſt vpon yours in this important matter of iuſtification? The ſaid A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle laboring to win the Romaines to the ſame faith, readeth them this lecture to the ſame effect.<note place="margin">Ro. 6, 23</note> 
               <hi>The wages of ſinne is death, but the guift of God is eternall life through Ieſus Chriſt our ſauiour:</hi> Heere you are plainly told what are the cauſes of going to hell, and comming to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. The deſert of man the cauſe of damnation, but the mercy of God the cauſe of ſaluation; our ſinne doth incur the one, <hi>for the reward of ſinne is death:</hi> but our beſt deſerts merit not the other, for, <hi>eternal life is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the guift of God through Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> had <hi>Paule</hi> that learned Apoſtle, in this point approued the doctrine of your church thus [queſtionleſſe] or to this effect, he would haue concluded, the reward of ſinne is death, and the reward of good workes is eternall life: but you ſee hee quite ouerthroweth that opinion, leauing vs of our ſelues to deſerue the one, but aſcribing the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Gods free guifte in Chriſt beyond our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert.</p>
            <p>But if neither of theſe places haue power to remoue you from your former opinion, giue me leaue to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce one ſaying more out of the ſame authour, which I aſſure my ſelfe [ſo you ponder it rightly] will pierce euen the quickeſt vayne of your heart, if the ſame [as I hope in my ſauiour it is not] be not vtterly benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb facs="tcp:21484:17"/>
               <hi>the ſufferings</hi> [ſaith he] <hi>of this life are not worthy of the glory to come.</hi> I conceiue that the workes whereby you hope to merit at Gods hands are the workes of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and workes of ſuffering, the former more eaſie, and leſſe deſeruing, the latter leſſe eaſie, and therefore (as you are taught] the more meritorious: but <hi>Paule</hi> that knew what it was both to do &amp; ſuffer, better then thoſe by whom you are perſwaded to place ſuch hie affiance in your workes, preacheth vnto you heere another kind of doctrine, namely that euen the ſufferings of this life, your afflictions, your deeds of beſt deſert, are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the glory to come. And you may be aſſured that no man that euer fought vnder the banner of Chriſt Ieſus ſuffered more for his ſake, or deſerued heauen bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for his ſufferings then he that teacheth you this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For he teſtifieth of himſelfe that the ſufferings of Chriſt did abound in him. <hi>That in labours, he was more aboundant then other in ripes aboue meaſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Co. 11, 23</note> 
               <hi>in pryſon more plenteouſly, on death oft, that of the Iewes fiue tymes he receiued forty ſtripes ſaue one, that he was thrice beaten with rods, once ſtoned, thrice ſuffered ſhrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, that he was night and day in the deepe Sea; In iournying often, in perils of waters, in perils of robbers, in perils of his owne nation, in perils among the gentiles, in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils in the citty, in perils in the wilderneſſe, in perils in the Sea, in perils amongſt falſe breathren, In wearineſſe and painefulneſſe, in watching often, In hunger and thirſt, in faſting often; In cold and in nakedneſſe, and beſide the thinges that were outward he was combred daiely, and had the eare of all the Churches.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phi 1, 13</note> 
               <hi>And that his bandes in Chriſt were famous throughout all the iudgement hall, and in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21484:17"/>
            <p>Theſe are <hi>Paules</hi> owne wordes of himſelfe, and his ſufferings. Now if euer there were ſuch merit in our works, ſure heere it was: if euer the deſert of ſinfull man could iuſtly haue challenged ſuch a reward as euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, doubtleſſe, <hi>Paule</hi> for theſe his ſufferinges would haue put in with the formoſt: Howbeit you ſee when he ſpeakes of the glory to come, and the proper cauſe of our attayning vnto eternall ſaluation, he then diſclaimeth from al his works, from theſe his ſufferings and all; and cherefully runs to another refuge euen the righteouſneſſe of his ſauiour chriſt Ieſus, wherein there is true merit indeede, and wherewith hee knovveth the iuſtice of God is worthily ſatiſfied, and our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall peace onely procured; thus you ſee what this holy Apoſtle of chriſt Ieſus thought touching this poynt of mans meriting; And I pray you marke how firmely the learned Fathers of the church cleaue vnto the ſame doctrine: My firſt place out of <hi>Paule</hi> was that wee are ſaued not by &amp;c. And Saint <hi>Ierom,</hi> one whom your church highly reuerenceth, writeth in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;<note place="margin">Hier: lib: 1, ad, Pelag</note> 
               <hi>Then are wee iuſt, when wee confeſſe our ſelues to be ſinners: And our iuſtice conſiſteth not of our owne merit but of Gods mercy:</hi> Heere this holy father in the matter of iuſtification, reiecteth with S. <hi>Paule</hi> all our owne merit, and referreth the ſame wholly to Gods mercy. My ſecond place out of the Apoſtle was, that <hi>the Wages of ſinne is death, but the guift of GOD is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life through &amp;c. Origene</hi> one of the moſt aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers of the church in expoſition of theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words, of <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith thus,<note place="margin">Origen in ep, ad, Ro: ca, 4, lib, 4</note> 
               <hi>The apoſtle ſaith that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ſin is death, but he added not &amp; ſaid likewiſe the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of iuſtice is eternall life, but he ſayeth eternall life is
<pb facs="tcp:21484:18"/>the gratious guift of God, to teach vs that wages which is like to debt, and reward is a recompence of pun ſhment and death, and to aſsigne eternall life to grace onely.</hi> Thus you heare this reuerent father expoundeth Paule, that our wickednes iuſtly meriteth condemnation, but that the ballaunce wanteth waight the other way, and that our beſt deedes merite not ſaluation, which is aſſigned to grace only; and if only to grace, then are all our workes abſolutely excluded in that buſines.</p>
            <p>My laſt place out of paule was, <hi>The ſufferings &amp;c.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to this, ſayeth Saint <hi>Barnard</hi> on this manner. <hi>Now concerning eternal life, we know the ſufferings of this life are not worthy of the glory to come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Barn. in Anunt Mariae. Serm. 1</note> 
               <hi>no not if one man ſhould ſuffer all,</hi> heere this deuout and religious father remoueth all doubt touching the former doctrine by a forcible ſuppoſition on this manner. Admit that the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and perſecutions of <hi>Paule,</hi> of <hi>Peter,</hi> of <hi>Iames,</hi> and all the Apoſtles, that the paine and torments of the <hi>Primitiue Church,</hi> and of thoſe fiue and twenty Byſhops which ſucceſſiuely were martyred for the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. And that all the tortures and ſufferings of all the Saints of God in allages from the death of <hi>Abell,</hi> to the laſt drop of blood that euer ſhal be ſhed vpon the earth for the teſtimony of the Lords truth were laide vppon one man to beare, and that it were poſſible for him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vnder go the paines, torments, and tortures, that they all indured, yet were the glorye of eternall life to rich a guerdon for thoſe his ſufferinges, hee coulde not merite heauen thereby, for the infinite iuſtice of God, muſt haue a greater ſatisfaction. This was the holy fathers cenſure hereupon, <hi>No not</hi> [ſaith he] <hi>if one man ſhould ſuffer all.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21484:18"/>
            <p>Now let me reaſon with you by an inuincible and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar argument, if the ſuffrings of Paule, or of anye of theſe holy martyres, whoſe continuall perſecutions and torments, were inſteed of many deaths vnto them. Nay, if all their paines, tortures and deaths, ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, would not make vp a deſert anſwearable to the meed of euerlaſting glory: It muſt needes followe that your deeds and ſufferings, which cary no neerer a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with the other, then your ſpan doth with the ſpatiouſnes of the whole earth, can merit no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſhall neuer for any deſert they are of, come home ſo rewarded No, no you muſt not look for ſuch an inrichment after ſuch a reckoning, but rather ſaye with the ſame Saint <hi>Barnard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm, 1 anunt. Mar</note> whom your ſelues confes to be one of the ſweeteſt quereſters in the Lords quier, <hi>What are all our merits to ſo great glory?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The gardens of all the Fathers of the Church, are thicke ſet with theſe flowers, they all of them teach [if true vnderſtood] the ſelfe ſame doctrine. Thus you heare then what the Scriptures and Fathers haue deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere touching our iuſtification, how they referre the ſame wholy to the mercy and grace of God in the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of Chriſt Ieſus, and ſhake off our owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, as hauing no hand in that worke nor worthineſſe in that degree to be truſted vnto.</p>
            <p>But fearing leaſt you are made beleeue that the Scriptures as we read them are falſe, and the Fathers as we vſe to alledge them but wreſted, [as what will not falſhood affirme, to diſcountenance the trueth, or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror be aſhamed to ſay for her owne ſhelter] I will yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt another meane, which I aſſure my ſelfe will cool, and am in good hope vtterly extinguiſhe that your
<pb facs="tcp:21484:19"/>conceit of merritting, and it ſhal be by making knowne vnto you the wonderfull inconuenience you incurre, and the dangerous premunire that your ſoule runs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by holding your workes in ſuch eſtimation.</p>
            <p>There are two principall vertues, whereby our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions God vouchſafeth to manifeſt himſelf to the know ledge of his ſeruants vpon the earth, and wherin it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his diuine omnipotency to be delighted, and they are his mercy and his Iuſtice. There are likewiſe 2. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall offices, which our mercifull Sauiour daigned to vndertake for our ſakes, whereby the fauour of God, which our old notorious pranke had eſtranged, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaind vnto vs, and thorough the bleſſed means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we are not onely become gratious with him in this world, but haue aſſurance of his ſight, and the happye fruition of eternall felicity in the worlde to come, and thoſe are his redeemerſhippe, and mediatorſhippe: and I pray you what will you thinke of your Religion, if the ſame, nay if one branch thereof among twenty, as rotten as it ſelfe, if this onely point of attributing merit to your workes, in the act of your iuſtification, doeth impaire and manifeſtly obſcure the dignitie of theſe excellent proprieties of God his mercie, and his Iuſtice, and withall diſparage, and apparantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from the Worthyneſſe of <hi>Christ</hi> his merite in that his redeemerſhippe, and mediatourſhippe; if your religion [I ſay] be guilty of ſuch heinous trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt the diuine Maieſty, will you not then iudge it your ſecureſt courſe to abandon her daungerous fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, and embrace [inſteed therof] for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort true chriſtianity, of whome you ſhall be ſure to learne nothing but true faith, and true obedience to
<pb facs="tcp:21484:19"/>your heauenly Soueraigne: In diſcouery hereof it is behoouefull for you to conceiue, that as the eſſence of God is infinite and perfect, ſo theſe proprieties of God his mercy and Iuſtice [becauſe they are eſſentiall in him] muſt likewiſe of neceſſity, be perfect and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite: which being graunted, doeth not euery opinion that ſhall intimate defect or inſufficiency therein, impaire [as I ſaide,] and manifeſtly obſcure the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof? you cannot denie but it doth, neither ſhall you euer be able ſubſtantially to cleere your doctrine of merites, from this high and perillous imputation. For looke how much you attribute to your owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in the purchaſe of ſaluation: So much you detract away from Gods mercy in Chriſt, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and onely price, whereby the ſame is purchaſed: <hi>God which is rich in mercy</hi> [ſaith <hi>Paule</hi>] <hi>through his great loue wherewith he loued vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſphe. 2, 4.</note> 
               <hi>euen when we were dead in ſinne, hath quickened vs together in Chriſt, for by grace are ye ſaued, and hath raiſed vs vp together, and made vs ſit together in heauenly things, through Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> And in another place formerly alledged, <hi>God hath not ſaued vs for the deeds of righteouſneſſe which we haue wrought, but of his mercy hath he ſaued vs.</hi> Heere the mercye of God appeareth like it ſelfe, Paule giueth it his due, and maketh it the only doer of the matter of ſaluation: you on the contrary, beleeue that you ſhal be ſaued by your works only, or at leaſt by your works &amp; this grace cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled togither: heer the mercy of god is ſhewed forth vnlike it ſelfe, you rob it of his due, making it either no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, as when you wil be iuſtified meerly by your own deeds without it, or at leaſt but a partner with you, when your deeds muſt draw in the ſame yoke with it, as coaiutors or fellow workers in that buſines.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21484:20"/>
            <p>Aſſure you ſelfe therefore, that the perfect and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy of our good and gratious God, doth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the imaginary merit of fleſh and blood, but is [and that not a little] indignified, by this groſſe and preſumptuous doctrine; for doe but ſeriouſly ponder with your ſelfe, whether that mercy can be infinit, that hath neede of a ſupplement, and how it can be perfect, when it muſt be eeked out with deedes of imperfection: yet is it perfect, and infinite, and ſhall euer remaine ſo, let neuer ſo many millions of your merit founders de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thereof as ill as they can, by ſuch their confiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in their owne deſeruinges. The ſame indignity you profer to the iuſtice of God, which being likewiſe [as his mercy is] perfect and infinite: you hope neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe will be ſatiſfied with corrupted intigrety, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed with your poluted righteouſneſſe: but you are as wide from the truth as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, for there is no iuſtice that can ſtand againſt the iuſtice of God, but that which carrieth proportion anſwearable therunto. It requireth an entire and ful paiment; And it is not the low-prized droſſe of <hi>Egypt,</hi> our ſtained &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure actions, but the refined gold of <hi>Saba,</hi> the vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and pure righteouſneſſe of chriſt Ieſus, that in the great day of our accompt will paſſe for currant. No no you ſhould be ſo far from arrogating vnto your ſelfe, any ability to the anſwering of that ſo infinite, and aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful iuſtice of God almighty, as rather firmely, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to reſt aſſured, that the vprightnes of al the men on earth, though the ſame indeede [reſpectiuely] be pleaſing, and acceptable vnto God, nor the integrity of all the Angels of heauen, yet I know they excell in ſtrength, and are now confirmed from euer falling: nor
<pb facs="tcp:21484:20"/>the holineſſe of all the Saintes, both in heauen, and in earth, [albeit I confeſſe they make vp that church, which chriſt himſelfe calleth faire, and without ſpot, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noreth beſide with the title of his ſiſter, his loue his ſpouſe, his doue, and his vndefiled. That the vprightnes [I ſay] integrity, and holineſſe of all theſe Angels and ſaints, nay the power of all their deſert ioyned together, cannot calme the tempeſt of Gods iuſtice from ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring downe indignation vpon all the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> for their originall and actuall tranſgreſſion, nor ſo much as qualifie the ſaid iuſtice towards your ſelfe in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, nor make a condigne ſatiſfaction for your ſins only, no not for the leaſt ſinne though you extenuate and mince it to the leaſt of your veniall ſins, that euer you committed; for any ſinne is a breach of the whole law, and who knoweth not the tranſgreſſion of the law is that proper act of rebellion, whereby this infinite iuſtice is ſo worthily incenſed, as without an infinite ſatiſfaction neuer to be apeaſed: yet are you bold of your ſelfe to ruſh in vpon that diſpleaſed maieſty, and hauing no lawfull warrant to preſent the ſame with an hollow bird of your owne worthineſſe: but you haue often heard that it is ill dallieng with ſaints, and let me by the way aduiſe you to beware how you ieſt any more with ſuch edg-tooles as Gods iuſtice: Howbeit your doctrine of merites for all theſe wronges, both to the mercye and Iuſtice of God, doth not yet finde lymits to bound his outrage in, but breaketh out further to ouerflow euen the obedience, and ſufferinges of our mercifull ſauior chriſt Ieſus, and as much as lieth in the handes of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie to annihilate his bleſſed righteouſneſſe the very truth only and al-ſufficient act of our redemption.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21484:21"/>
            <p>This righteouſneſſe of chriſt, (which none but the rabble of Antichriſt will deny) you muſt vnderſtand is perfect: And it is neceſſary it ſhould be ſo, for it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countereth the perfect iuſtice of god, and is layed in the ballance to waygh againſt the ſame for a wonderfull va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew, a valew of no leſſe worth then the welfar, and whole eſtate of euery chriſtian ſoule, that euer was, or euer ſhall be impriſoned in the corrupt tabernacle of fleſh and blood. Now, you not contented to ſet down your whole reſt vpon the ſufficiency of this righteouſneſſe, either pull the ſame quite out of the ballance, and put in ſteede thereof your own, or at leaſt lay yours vpon his to make vp the waight, as though the other were ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: wherein what derogation you proffer to the merit of chriſts obedience, it is moſt manifeſt, the ſame being of it ſelfe ſo abſolute, and what madnes you ſhew therin may be wondered at, when al your merits vnto chriſts, are [for ſubſtance] not a drop to the maine Ocean, and [for waight] not ſo much as a feather, to the whole earth. The ſpirit of truth that holy charmer himſelfe wil quickly reſolue you herein, if [Adderlike] you ſtop not your eares againſt him, as [methinks] you ſhould not, howſoeuer you be inioyned by man, becauſe he alwaies charmeth moſt wiſely:<note place="margin">Eſay, 63, 3</note> In one place <hi>Chriſt alone hath troden down the winepreſſe neither was there any at al that helped him. God forbid that I ſhould reioyce in any thing but in the croſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gala. 6, 14,</note> 
               <hi>death and paſſion, of our Lord Ieſus chriſt. The blood of Ieſus chriſt the ſon of God clenſeth vs from all ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh, 1, 7</note> Now if chriſt aloue hath troden down that preſſe that would haue preſſed vs to death: If we muſt reioyce in nothing, but only in the death of chriſt Ieſus: If the precious blood of that ſweete ſauiour of ours, doth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:21484:21"/>clenſe vs from all our ſins, what ſhould we thinke of our ſelues, and of our works? What haue we to do, that of our ſelues are but worms of the earth in compariſon? What haue our works to do, that of themſelues are but meere vnworthines in the ſight of the almighty? What [I ſay] haue we or our works to do in this high, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy office of our ſaluation? It is already mercifully vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, by him that could performe it for vs: It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready happily performed by him that did vndertake it for vs, and being ſo vndertaken, and performed to our hands, what remaineth now for vs, but faithfully to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him that hath done theſe wonders for the children of men, and next of all holily to liue in him, becauſe he commaundeth vs to be holy as he is holy; and were it but to expreſſe our thankefulnes for ſuch his vnſpeakeable mercies towards vs. Yet ſo to beleeue &amp; liue in him, as that we neuer beleue we can do any thing while vve liue that ſhall vvorthy vs to pertake with him in the memorable act of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or can haue power [though iſſuing from the greateſt perfection of humain ability to merit the reward of eternall glory. For if we cold, then this our bleſſed redeemer did put on the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy garment of our humanity in vain, did keep the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements in vaine, did ſweate water, and blood in vaine, did want the priuiledge euen of little ſparrowes for his repoſe in vaine, and ſubmitted himſelfe to all his ſufferinges from the Manger, which was his cradle, to the croſſe, which was the concluſion of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and all this he vnderwent for our loue in vain, if we be able to merit of our ſelus, if we haue holines to make our own peace, for ſo he hath done nothing for vs, but vvhat vve can do of our ſelues, which were a horrible &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:21484:22"/>blaſphemous concluſion: and yet you ſee reaſonably drawne from this your ſacriligious and ſo derogatory doctrine of merits.</p>
            <p>And yet derogatory further, for it leaueth not our Sauiour heere, but ſecondeth this iniury of his redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſhip with changing the natur of his mediatorſhip: For what is a mediator amongſt men, or chriſt as he is mediatour betwixt God and man, but a traueller, or one that interpoſeth himſelfe betweene ſeuerall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to make peace, betweene the offended, and the offendor: The partie heer offended is God, by reaſon of ſinne committed, the partie offender is man, that hath committed this ſinne againſt him. God is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly iuſt, and will not be put off with ſhifts, but ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon ſatisfaction. Man is a ſtark bankerout, clean blown out, and hath nothing wherewith to ſatisfie. O bleſſed God that art ſo righteous in all thy workes, and thrice bleſſed be thy holy name, euen for being ſo iuſt that thou wilt be ſatisfied; but O curſed man that was ſo wicked in his waies, as to forſake his gratious God, that had made him ſo rich, and [when he might haue choſen] to plunge himſelfe in ſuch extreame pouerty: Methinkes I ſee him ſoeing figge-leaues to couer his ſhame, and ſhuddering himſelfe behind trees, from the preſence of the Almightie: methinks I heare him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing the Lord friuilouſly, and prating out excuſes to no purpoſe; for God that it is truth it ſelf, and ſeeth all things cannot be deluded.</p>
            <p>And yet methinks, lifting vp my ſelf, I ſee another arm of mercy extended forth to ſaue, as wel as that arm of Iuſtice to deſtroy: I ſee the Lord is merciful, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, long ſuffering, and of great goodnes, that he wil
<pb facs="tcp:21484:22"/>not alway be chiding, nor continue his anger for euer, that he dealeth not with his ſeruants after their ſinnes, nor rewardeth them according to their wickednes. In a word, which is my ſouls rauiſhing comfort, methinks I ſee his mercy without impeachment to his Iuſtice, to ſhine aboue al his works, for with this arme of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he taketh this ſinner vp, and euen him himſelf tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough his wiſedome, and power deuiſeth a means to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie himſelfe, and reſtore againe the poore offender to his fauour.</p>
            <p>And now my ſweet Sauiour, I muſt returne againe vnto thee, for the needle of my ſoule truely touched [I hope] with thy grace, wil neuer ſtand ſtill, till it come directly againſt thy merit, the fixed point of my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>When man by ſinne had thus ſeperated himſelf from his maker, and the iawes of eternall damnation [but a deſerued guerdon] gaped wide to haue ſwallowed him vp, at this dead lift Chriſt Ieſus, (by whom all thinges formerly were made,) commeth to help out, and draw together againe, his father and this offender, that ſtood in ſuch oppoſition; he vndertaketh to pay the debt, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a certaine day, and keepeth it, &amp; requireth nothing of this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for whom thus frendly he becam paimaiſter but before till the day came, to beleeue in him that he would pay it: and after, when the day was paſt, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him that he had payed it, and before and after to loue him for his labour, and obſerue that courſe for his life [as neere as he could] which he preſcribed him. But what is all this [ſaith the cauiller] to Chriſtes me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatorſhip: I might anſweare, that it is but a profitable digreſſion at moſt, but I will anſweare it is no digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:21484:23"/>at all: For I aſſure you it is ſo pertinent, ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily belonging thereunto, that if you knowe not this you knowe nothing, if you perfectly conceiue not this, you ſhall neuer thoroughly vnderſtande the other: and now I beſeech you learne to knit them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>When chriſt the ſecond perſon in the Trinity the very ſonne of God, and yet perfect God himſelfe, had for the ſufficient and more proper diſcharge of this debt for man, which man by no means could haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged for himſelfe, aſſumed our humanity, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly ſatisfied the wrath of God as aforeſaide: In due time he forſooke the earth, and returned vnto the bleſſed boſome of his father from whence hee came, and becauſe he knew that man for all this kindneſſe ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed him, would not be fully reclaimed, nor thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purged during his abode vpon earth of that perniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humor of diſobedience that poſſeſſed him, but ſtil be prone to offend, and from time to time prouoking his Lorde and maker to indignation againſt him: Hee there in heauen ſeated vppon that glorious throne of Maieſty and power, the right hande of his Father, continually intreateth, preſenteth ſatisfaction, and vndertaketh for him, I meane his Seruaunts that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully beleeue in him, and truely depend vppon his righteouſneſſe for their ſaluation, and therein I praye you conceiue that his mediatorſhippe (as with God the party offended) doth principally now conſiſt; I ſay in intreating, preſenting ſatisfaction, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking for vs; For he intreateth his father to take pitty of vs, albeit we deſerue it not, to loue vs although wee haue not loued him, and to embrace vs for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:21484:23"/>notwithſtanding our diſobedience towardes him, and becauſe being God as well as man, in this his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of mediatorſhippe, it concerneth him to ſee the Iuſtice of God fully ſatisfied, before his mercy be thus thoroughly extended: In his petition he compriſeth effectuall conſiderations to ſtirre vppe compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, namely in regarde of his obedience and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feringes in our ſteede, for his righteouſnes ſake, which he continually preſenteth vnto his father, as a ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for our ſinnes, and prayeth that the ſame may be accepted for vs, and we for the merit thereof become acceptable and gratious in his ſight for euer: And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he vndertaketh that at length, we ſhal leaue our ſins, and ceaſe to offend his deuine Maieſty any more, that wee ſhall truely honour him, and become fit inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to ſound forth his praiſe and glory.</p>
            <p>Now I beſeech you mark how this doctrin of Chriſts mediatorſhip, and your doctrin of merits can ſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither. Chriſt as a mediator intreteth his father in our behalfe, but if we do merit what need this intreaty, for God is iuſt, and of himſelf wil reward the wel deſeruing of euery man to the ful: Chriſt as he is a mediator, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth ſatisfaction vnto his father for our ſinnes, but if we do merit, that ſatisfaction might be ſpared, for God is iuſt, &amp; wil not be paid duble: chriſt as he is our medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, vndertaketh for our innocency herafter, but if we do merit, then belike we are innocent already, for none can merit at gods hands that is abſolute righteouſnes, but he that is abſolutely righteous, and ſo that part of chriſts mediatorſhip would ceaſe, for God is iuſt, and will haue no ſecurity, for that heerafter which he hath receiued already: but what doctrin cal you this? and yet
<pb facs="tcp:21484:24"/>ſuch is your doctrine of merits, and ſo derogating as you ſee from the holy mediatorſhip of chriſt Ieſus: If therefore you looke for benifit by that mediatorſhip [as moſt miſerable is their condition that do not] you muſt lay by your own merit, which is ſo thin a clothing, that the leaſt drop of Gods indignation will drench cleane through it; and cloath your ſelfe with chriſtes merit, which will keepe you warme indeed, and be ſure to hold out in all weather: for as chriſt came from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen into the world, not to call the righteous (they that thinke themſelues ſo) but the ſinners [they that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge themſelues ſo] to repentance. In like ſort he returned not into heauen out of the world to medy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate for ſuch pharaſaicall iuſticiaries, as reſt vpon their owne integrity, but for the humble deiected publicans, that with repentance acknowledge their owne vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe.</p>
            <p>Furthermore I do not ſee, how it can be well main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, but that it is in ſome ſort repugnant euen to the office of the holy ghoſt likewiſe: for if the ſame be to ſanctifie vs to nevvneſſe of life, and to giue groweth to our faith from time to time, which taken at the beſt [as I am taught] ſtandeth in neede of increaſe: how can any workes we do, which are the fruites of that faith, be truely ſayd to merit, conſidering it is a ground, that the effect muſt be anſwerable to the cauſe, and the cauſe heer which is our faith, being deſectiue, the effect which is our workes cannot bee perfect as neceſſarily they muſt be, if they be meritorious: now tel me I pray you, whether any hereſie can be compact of groſſer abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities then this, be more preiudiciall then this, or the author of greater indignity euen to the bleſſed Trinity,
<pb facs="tcp:21484:24"/>then proceedeth from this your hereſie of merits: and yet which may be wondered at, it findeth profeſſors and patrons more then a good many, and thoſe ſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe not vnlearned, but profoundly reade in all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that humane helpes can puffe vp their vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with: but there is a knowledge that only one ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter reueileth; a diuine knowledge, a diuine ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter, happy and truely learned is that ſcholler, which is trained vp in ſuch knowledge, and that is inſtructed (how vnlearned ſoeuer he ſeeme otherwiſe) by ſuch a ſcholemaiſter.</p>
            <p>I am not altogether ignorant of the cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which your greateſt clarkes deuiſe for maintenance of this your merit, and how they will haue their merit of worke, and merit of the perſon, the merit of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity, and the merit of condignity, and I knowe they will tell you, that there are diuers places of ſcripture to vphold the ſame. But firſt let me tell you what a bold of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, a good-fellow of our church once made to the contrary, he that can ſhew me
[ſaith he] in any ſcripture that workes do merit, or be any meanes to our iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the firſt ſcripture, without any further iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I will looſe both mine eares; for the ſecond, my tongue, for the third my neck; but the yſſue was, they accepted of his eares, his tongue, and his neck, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out performing the condition, for no ſuch place in all the whole ſcripture could be found; and yet was he pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully martyred amongſt them, poore ſoule, nay rich ſoule rather, for who can be richer then he, by whom euen the houſe of God is inriched, and it is the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a learned father, that <hi>the blood of the martyr is the ſeede of the Church:</hi> I confeſſe there are many ſayinges
<pb facs="tcp:21484:25"/>in the booke of god, that at the firſt ſight, and being not throughly waighed, do ſeeme to import ſuch a matter, as where it is ſaid that <hi>euery man ſhall receiue according to his labour: your reward is great in heanen; he will render to euery man according to his works.</hi> From theſe and ſuch places, your doctors would draw inuincible arguments that good workes, becauſe God hath promiſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them, doe therefore merit that reward ſo promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but there is no neceſſity of that conſequent; our good workes indeed ſhall receiue reward, but not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they merit the ſame: for the fineſt hath his ſtaine, &amp; the beſt worke that man can doe is blemiſhed: but in regard that God of his owne free grace and mercy, without reſpect to any worthyneſſe in the worke at all, hath promiſed to reward them, who being euer faithful, will euer be as good as his promiſe, and ſhew himſelfe in all thinges to deale with his ſeruantes that truely depend vpon his mercy, far better then after their beſt deſeruings. And that our workes deſerue not this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, chriſt that is the paymaiſter himſelfe, by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Doni, 9.38</note> by himſelfe telleth vs plainely, <hi>We do not</hi> [ſaith the prophet] <hi>preſent or ſupplications be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3, 27</note> 
               <hi>for our owne righteouſneſſe but for thy great ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies: your reioycing</hi> [ſaith the apoſtle] <hi>is excluded by the law of faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 37 10.</note> 
               <hi>When ye haue don all</hi> (ſaith chriſt) <hi>ſay, we are vnprofitable ſeruants.</hi> The reuerent fathers and and learned Doctors of the church are copyous, and doe flow in their obſernations, vpon theſe and ſuch like places of holy write, to drowne the barren plot of mans merits, &amp; bring in greater eſtimation, the <hi>Aeden</hi> ſoile of chriſts righteouſnes where all true merits grow, and whence the riches euen of heauen it ſelfe are to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered:
<pb facs="tcp:21484:25"/>but becauſe I haue already partly cited them vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame ſubiect, and my letter begins with prolixity to try the pacience euen of a friendly reader: I will only preſent you with a litle noſegaie of foure or fiue flowers out of their ſeuerall Gardens, which
[although for haſt they be not curiouſly tyed together] will neuertheleſſe I doubt not yeeld your ſoule, a ſweete and delectable ſent, if you neglect them not, and with a conceipt of their vnworthineſſe caſt them not behind you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is the onely perfection of men if they know themſelues to be vnperfect.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Pelag. Auguſtine in manua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ca, 22</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All my hope is in the death of my Lord: His death is my merit, my refuge, ſaluation life, and reſurrection; my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is the compaſsion of my Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs hope for forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes as of faith in chriſt, and not of debt as due for any merit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſe lib. 2. ad Poeniten, c 8</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euery man ſhall be rewarded according to his works, but not for his workes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gregorie in Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1, 4, 2 Barnardde liber. arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tr,</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To ſpeake properly of thoſe workes which we call our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, they are but the ſeede-plats of hope, the tokens of our predeſtination, the preſagers of our future happineſſe, the way to the kingdome, not the cauſe of raigning there: To conclude whom God hath iuſtified, not thoſe whom he found iuſt, he hath glorified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will make vp this poſie with one flower more out of the Garden of the ſaid S. <hi>Bernard</hi> which I knowe you will hold deere for her ſake whoſe name is written vpon it, whom you eſteeme to be [and while you ſay no other wiſe of her I will ſay with you] the moſt bleſſed Virgin that euer bare life.<note place="margin">Bar. Scr. 1 Anunt. ma</note> 
               <hi>Let them</hi> [ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>] <hi>ſeeke for merit that liſt, It is beſt for vs to ſtudy to find grace,</hi> then he ſheweth this reaſon, for <hi>Mary ſtandeth not vpon her me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit but ſeeketh grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21484:26"/>
            <p>Now, if the Virgin Mary whome you make no leſſe then a Goddeſſe, whom you cal the Queene of heauen, the Queen of the world, and mother of grace and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; whome you account a generall aduocate for all Gods ſeruants vpon the earth, whom you inuocate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day, whoſe honor you celebrate at eight ſolemne feaſts euery yeare, and to whome you giue power to commaunde Chriſt her ſonne, and to commaund him by the authority of a Mother. For al which [&amp; did you heap as many more glittering titles together, as there are Starres in the firmament] I am perſwaded ſhe will neuer giue you thankes, for ſhe loueth her ſonne, her Lord, her God, too wel, to take vnto her ſelfe any thing that is due vnto him, or to ſmile vpon thoſe that ſhall rob him of his honour, and giue it to any other, thogh it be to her ſelfe: If ſhee [I ſay] as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, pretendeth not her owne merit, but reſteth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the grace and mercy of God her Sauiour: What doe you thinke it beſt for you to do? You acknowledge your ſelfe I knowe inferiour to her, in workes, in grace, and euery way; yet be not contrary to her in workes, or grace, or any way: forſake not the grace of GOD, which is all in all, to fly ynto your owne merite, which is nothing, for then you are contrarie to her; but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the merit of your owne workes, that hath no ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity in it, and fly vnto the grace of God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is powerfull to ſaue your ſoule, and ſo you are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to her, for then ſhe becommeth your happy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, ſhe is therein vnder the bleſſed ſpirit, your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Schoole miſtres.</p>
            <p>You little thought [I dare anſwere for you] that any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſhe had helde [at leaſt in ſuch a materiall poynt
<pb facs="tcp:21484:26"/>of ſaluation] had bene contrary, or ſo much as repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the doctrine, which is eſtabliſhed in the church of Rome: For as you haue bone taught, that ſhe was without ſin, becauſe ſhe bare the ſauior of the worlde, ſo are you borne in hand, that the ſaid doctrine is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out errour, becauſe it is eſtabliſhed by thoſe that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre. But eronious are they that whiſper theſe things in your eares, and ſimple are you that lend ſuch liſtning thereunto, for God hath taught both them and you another leſſon,<note place="margin">Galat 3, 22</note> namely that <hi>the ſcripture hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded all</hi> [not excluding the virgin Mary] <hi>vnder ſinne:</hi> And that <hi>euery man</hi> (not excepting the <hi>Pope</hi>) <hi>is a lyer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3, 4</note> But to touch theſe points otherwiſe then by the waye, you might thinke were by the purpoſe. The matter in hand is merit of workes, and I hope I haue ſufficiently indeared the contrary doctrin vnto you. Howbeit, that potent obiection of yours [as you take it] that becauſe God hath promiſed ſuch a rewarde vnto vs, if we doe good workes, therefore our good workes deſerue that reward: I wil auoid another way by diſcouering the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth thereof by a playne, and familiar example.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe I pray you, that an earthly king ſhould ſay to one of his ordinary ſeruants, do ſuch a thinge, and I will giue thee ſuch an Earledome for thy labour: and that this ſeruant when he hath perfourmed that which was commaunded him (although the ſame belonged to his place] and that he ſtoode bounde to doe it before, ſhoulde [notwithſtanding] expect this great rewarde from the King, as being due vnto him for the little pain hee had taken, and as though the very doing of that ſmall matter had deſerued it. What would you thinke of ſuch a ſeruant? woulde you think him well in his wits?
<pb facs="tcp:21484:27"/>or at leaſt well worthy of ſuch aduancement, I knowe you would not, but rather iudge him an vnthankefull body, and hold it pitty that ſuch preferment ſhoulde be beſtowed vppon one, that would ſo abuſe his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters bounty. Say you ſo? Why then [although I am no prophet as <hi>Nathan</hi> was] I may take you as <hi>Nathan</hi> tooke <hi>Dauid</hi> in your owne anſweare, and ſay vnto you, Thou art the party. God hath commaunded you to do good workes, and yet no other then belong vnto your calling, and ſuch as by the band of your election, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, redemption, and adoption, [I hope and iudge the beſt of you] you are bounde vnto, and for the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, he promiſeth you the rewarde of eternall glory. Now admit you do theſe good workes, as God commaundeth you, and when you haue done them, thinke that for the merit thereof, you may expect your reward propoſed, are you not with the aforeſaide ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant very vnthankefull? Doe you not vtterly miſtake the matter, and attribute that vnto your owne merit, which is due vnto Goddes mercy? Queſtionleſſe you do, then how much more are you to be blamed, that hauing not done thoſe workes that the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth you, but being [at the beſt] an vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, ſhall [notwithſtanding] in lieu [as I may ſay] of your owne vnworthineſſe, and for the merit of that which you left vndone, look for the reward of eternall felicity.</p>
            <p>I will accompany this example, [for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the point, and becauſe I would come home, euen to the ſhalloweſt capacity] with three natural rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of impoſſibility, that you, or the godlieſt that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vpon the earth, ſhould merit ſaluation, as you &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:21484:27"/>all that liue after the doctrine of the church of Rome haue bin, and are continually miſinſtructed. The firſt reaſon is, the huge and wonderful debt that you alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die owe vnto God, at whoſe hands you thinke to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and of whom you muſt confeſſe commeth all ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Indeede, were you a cleere ground with him, did you owe him nothing, but had condignly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him for all the pleaſures he hath done you, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied him for all the trepaſſes you haue done vnto him: Then happily there might be ſome colour for ſuch an ability in you, then were the groſſenes of the opinion not all ſo palbable. But being ſo deepely indebted vnto him, I cannot particularize wherein, but would haue you conceyue it thus, for all that you are, for all that you haue receiued, that you haue not deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and for all that you haue not receiued, that you haue deſerued: All this being vpon your ſcore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, amounting [were it truely told] to ten thouſand Talents at leaſt, euery minute increaſing, and no means in you to cleere the ſame: how can you think to merit ought of him, to whom you ſtand thus ingaged? Is not all and more by much then you are able to doe by the conſiderations aforeſaide, due vnto him? How then is it poſſible, that the vttermoſt thinge you can doe,
[when the vttermoſt is not ſo much as you are bound to do] ſhould be merritorious with him, and ſo merritorious, as to purchaſe of him euerlaſting ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: you may aſſure your ſelfe, were there no other reaſon, but this only of the debt you owe him, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pay him, that it is impoſſible.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon is that your works, admit that they ſprang from true faith, which muſt giue them vertue, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:21484:28"/>worthy them the title of good workes, are not properly your owne, but Gods, and therefore it is impoſſible you ſhould deſerue your ſaluation by them: for can you thinke to merit ſuch a matter at the hands of God, for giuing him that which of right belongeth vnto him, and for preſenting him but with the fruite of his owne vineyard; you haue no foundation whereon to ground any ſuch an opinion: but Methinkes you take it very ſtrangely, that the good workes you do, ſhould not be your owne, and that without proofe thereof, you will not ſo eaſily be perſwaded thereunto. The holy apoſtle, and learned father, S <hi>Paule</hi> and S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> ſhall iuſtifie the ſame vnto you;<note place="margin">Phi, 2, 13</note> The one telleth you that <hi>it is God,</hi> [not your ſelfe] <hi>which worketh in you,</hi> not the wil one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but <hi>both the will and the deede:</hi> and in another place ſaith vnto you, as though he were angry with you for arrogating any goodneſſe vnto your ſelfe,<note place="margin">Ro: 4 : 7 Auguſtine Tract. 3 in Ioh.</note> 
               <hi>What haſt thou that thou haſt not receiued?</hi> The other [I meane] S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> aſſures you that <hi>god crowneth not you but his own gifts or graces which hehath giuen you,</hi> rewardes not your good workes, but his owne good workes in you. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then your workes whereby you hope to merit are not properly your owne but belonging vnto God, to whom you offer the ſame, you muſt needs confeſſe that by this reaſon likewiſe, it is impoſſible you ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue ought at the hand of God, much leſſe merit ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the doctrine of your church your owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p>My laſt reaſon of impoſſibility is, the diſproportion betwixt the vvorke you doe, and the reward you hope to acquire for doing the ſame; for if you vvill receiue one thing in lieu of another, if your deſeruings muſt
<pb facs="tcp:21484:28"/>gaine you the bleſſings of eternall life, It is neceſſary that thoſe merits of yours which you bring vnto God, be inſome ſort of equall value, or neere in worth to the benifits which you are to receiue from him; But do you know what compariſon there is betwixt gold, &amp; droſſe, the difference betwixt light and darkneſſe, or what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion there can be, betwixt perfection and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; ſuch a compariſon, ſuch difference, ſuch and no nearer a proportion there is betwixt the greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of the holyeſt ſaint vpon the earth, and the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, [if there be a difference of rewardes] beſtowed vpon the ſaints in heauen; For the ioyes of heauen are [as I know you will confeſſe] abſolutely perfect, inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and incomprehenſible: and you muſt vnderſtand that the works of the regenerate, ſuch as we call, and do beſt deſerue the title of good workes, although as they yſſued from the pure ſountaine of gods grace they bee perfectly cleare, &amp; vntainted, yet paſſing along through the furred pipes of the corrupted wiland vnderſtanding of man, they looſe ſome parte of their natiue purity, and proceede from him defiled and poluted. I may therefore conclude it impoſſible, that the one being ſo imperfect, ſhould merit the other of ſuch infinite per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>Further ſayings I might alleadge to the ſame effect, and make thoſe that I haue alledged
[if neede were] by familiar inſtance more perſpicuouſly to appeare vnto you. But that which I haue already ſaid to the point, is either ſufficient, or all that I can deuiſe to ſay, would be to no purpoſe: I haue proued vnto you that this doctrine of merits taught in your church is againſt the doctrine eſtabliſhed in chriſtes church; And by
<pb facs="tcp:21484:29"/>no leſſe pregnant reaſons then becauſe the apoſtle flatly condemneth it, becauſe the fathers vtterly diſclaime fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, becauſe thoſe excellent, and infinite proprieties of God, his mercy and iuſtice, are therein obſcured, the holy and bleſſed offices of chriſt his redeemerſhip, and mediatorſhip thereby infringed, that catholicke doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the holy ghoſt increaſing our faith, and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs to newneſſe of life, through the ſame (in ſome ſort) impugned, and finally becauſe it is repugnant e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to common ſence, and reaſon, and ſtandeth not with any poſſibility.</p>
            <p>I will ſtirre no further into the errours, nor rip vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more abſurdities of your religion: But for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, with my earneſt and moſt inſtant deſire impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune you, without preiudicate opinion, without fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceipting (after probabilities) my inſufficiency, to ſpeake ſubſtancially to matters of this nature: that you wold ſubdue your ſelfe to a ſerious and indifferent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of that which I haue ſaid, againſt this one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opinion of your religion. Shew your ſelfe a skilfull ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt heerin, and like the exquiſite Geometrician, that by the foote of <hi>Hercules,</hi> was able to deliniate the true ſhape of his whole body, ſo by this one point onely of mans merit, I pray learne iudiciouſly to obſerue what the whole ſubſtance is like to be of that which you call your catholicke religion. For if this one member [as you ſee the Apoſtle, and fathers haue giuen Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment] be rotten, what ſoundneſſe can you aſſure your ſelfe to find in the other parts that make vp the body of your profeſſion: if the doctrine of this point be ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicial to the mercy and inſtice of God your maker, ſo detractory from the redeemerſhip, and mediatorſhip
<pb facs="tcp:21484:29"/>of Chriſt your ſauior, ſo repugnant to the office of the holy ghoſt your ſanctifier, and finally ſo impoſſible: What infecting errors, nay what ſoule-bane hereſies, can the doctrine of all the other points of your religion be free from.</p>
            <p>There is an anſwerable proportion betwixt this and the reſt: Or if it fayle, it is in this degree, becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the other pointes haue not that colour of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance out of the ſcriptures, as this pointe of merites is vpheld by: For I confeſſe, there were ſundry places which vpon the firſt ſhew, and not well examined, did ſeeme a ſupportation for this opinion: but there are diuerſe other pointes of your religion, which haue not ſo much as any literall ſhew of countenance by the word of God: but are inforced to flye from the ſame, to crouch vnder the protection of <hi>Traditions,</hi> &amp; <hi>Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,</hi> and beg their defence from the warrant of ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine authority: ſo that in this regard the doctrine of moſt of the other points of your religion ſeemeth to be leſſe iuſtifiable, howſoeuer, yet full as vnſound, and as litle deſeruing to be truſted vnto, as this of the merit of your works in the act of your iuſtification: but I promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed [if I had not, I am compelled] to inſiſt vpon no other particular, and I hope it were needleſſe, for I doubt not but that which I haue ſaide touching this one point on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hath made you in ſome ſort to diſtaſt the reſt, and wrought in you at leaſt, a ſenſible feeling of your ſoules inſirmity.</p>
            <p>NOw it remaineth that after that poore skill I haue I preſcribe you ſome whole ſome courſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Sect.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this your dangerous maladye may be cured. For he
<pb facs="tcp:21484:30"/>may be a cunning, but cannot be a kinde Phyſitian, that hauing diſcourſed vnto his patient, [though but in part] the nature of her diſeaſe, and layed open vnto her [inſome meaſure] the daungerous eſtate ſhe is in, ſhall then preſently leaue her to her ſelfe, and regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of her recouery, affoord her no further comfort: To auoide therefore that imputation, which I woulde be loth by you, or any elſe, in this or any other expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment ſhould deſeruedly be laide vpon me: and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the method I preſcribed vnto my ſelfe in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, I wil firſt impart vnto you what the medicine is, that neceſſarily you muſt take. Secondly, ſome part of thoſe infinite and vnſpeakeable benefits, which you ſhall receiue in taking it. Thirdly, the meanes whereby you muſt take it. And laſtly, what little charge it will ſtand you in, and how cheape the taking of it, will bee vnto you: But becauſe my allowance of time is ſpent, and your patience I feare to ſore preſſed, I will huddle vp this which is behind, &amp; rather omit ſomthing that I could ſay, then be taxed for containing my ſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no compaſſe,</p>
            <p>In a word then, this medicine is a true and ſincere faith in the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt Ieſus. This fayth [if you remember) I haue formerly defined, and plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly laid down vnto you al the cauſes, and ſome of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof. It ſhall ſuffice in this place onely to tell you that it is, <hi>A ſpeciall and perfect aſſurance that we are partakers of the merit of Chriſtes righteouſneſſe, and that by the ſame righteouſneſſe onely ſatisfaction is made vnto God for all our offences, and our ſaluation purchaſed.</hi> This is that wholeſome receit, which I would miniſter vnto you, and this you may be bolde to take, for it will bee
<pb facs="tcp:21484:30"/>ſure to cure your ſoule, I gage mine owne vpon it, not onely of that peſtilent <hi>Gangrena,</hi> the merit of workes, but of all other imperfections, that now doe, or ſhall heereafter threaten the ruine thereof. This only might be a ſufficient motiue, to ſtir vp your deſire, to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it.</p>
            <p>But to make you more eager, vnderſtand more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the benefits that you ſhall reape by the ſame, It will make you that which you ſo long to be, <hi>A ſaued ſoule in heauen,</hi> So Saint <hi>Paule</hi> aſſureth you.<note place="margin">Ephe, 1, 1 Luke 6.20</note> It will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure you that which you ſo faine would haue, <hi>Forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all your ſinnes,</hi> So Saint <hi>Luke</hi> aſſureth you. It wil procure you that wherunto al the brauery and felicity of the earth, is traſh and beggery. <hi>Praiſe, honour, and glory at the ioyfull appearing of Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Peter. 1 Chap, 7</note> And ſo Saint <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe, whom I know you will beleeue, aſſureth you: Through this, you ſhal haue free acceſſe to the grace of God, which will make you eternally happye. Through this you ſhall reioyce in all your tribulations, which otherwiſe would make you vnhappy, &amp; through this like thoſe doubty ſouldiors of Chriſt that haue led you the waie, you ſhall ſhew your ſelfe a valiant cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, and ouercome the world: This will be a <hi>Superſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas</hi> vnto you, not onely againſt the eternall death, [as is already proued] but againſt the temporall death like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for the beleeuer, (although he ſeeme to be dead) is aliue, as the vnbeleeuer, [although he ſeeme to bee aliue is dead: God giueth [ſaith one] ſuch grace and priuiledge to faith, that death, which of his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the priuation of life, doth thereby become the entrance into life. This is that happy ſtarre which will lead you directly to that houſe where the king of glory
<pb facs="tcp:21484:31"/>hath his habitation: Nay what will you ſay if the virgin Mary, was not more happy for bearing the bleſſed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our Sauior, then you ſhall be by poſſeſſing this faith, whereby, [as by the inſtrumental cauſe] you muſt be ſaued: you thinke this a hard ſaying, as the caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naits thought that of chriſts, yet Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth no leſſe, for theſe are his wordes, <hi>Mary was more bleſſed in receiuing the faith of Christ, then ſhe was in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the fleſh of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt benefit of faith that I will propoſe vnto you, [omitting many which I know, and acknowledging in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite which I know not] is, that thereby your works wil becom good works, at leaſt accepted for good, &amp; from the leaſt to the greateſt, receiue their reward. Whereas, without the ſaid faith, there is no vertue in them, they taſt no more in gods mouth, then the white of an Egge doth in mans, they pleaſe him not, for without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe him: and indeed they are no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ſinnes, for (as I haue ſaide) whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſin. I know you think your works are good alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, &amp; better by many degrees then mine, and me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an vnfit ſchoolma. to read a lectur ther of vnto you. I refer that vnto him, who hath the balance in his hand, and humbly throw downe mine, ſuch as they are at the footſtool of his mercy, confeſſing that many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ſuch as I haue cauſe to be aſhamed of, and the beſt of them not ſo good as I long they were, and hope they will be: but to make you look with a ſingle and no ſuch indulgent eie vpon your owne, Vnderſtand that euery good work muſt neceſſarily haue theſe two ends, <hi>Faith, and the glory of God:</hi> faith is the end from whence it muſt proceed, The glory of God is the end wherunto it muſt
<pb facs="tcp:21484:31"/>be directed Now if the work want either of theſe ends, it is not a good worke, yours, want them both, for they cannot proceed from faith, which attributeth ſaluation wholy to the merit of chriſts righteouſneſſe, while you think that they in any degree, are meritorious of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, neither can they be directed to gods glory, when the principall matter, whereat you aime in doing them, is your owne aduantage. Now you muſt conceiue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that theſe two ends of good works faith and Gods glory are inſeperable. So that do your works from faith, and you cannot chooſe but do them to Gods glory, &amp; you ſhalbe ſure (though you doe them not in hope of reward) to receiue reward for doing them.</p>
            <p>The means whereby you muſt attaine vnto this faith, is earneſt praier, according to chriſtes preſcription, and attentiue hearing of the word of God. Touching the firſt, let me tell you that God many times ſeemeth to defer the giuing of his bleſſings, euen thoſe bleſſinges, which from al eternitie he hath determined to giue, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they be ſought for, and begged at his hands by prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. I vvill inſtance this only in our father <hi>Iſaac,</hi> to whom vvhen God, to expell his ſorrovv, for his deere decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mother, had giuen the comfort of a fair and louing wife, yet he gaue not yſſue, [<hi>Rebecka</hi> vvas a good while barren] vntil ſuch time as he betooke himſelf to praier for the ſame, and then the Lorde was intreated of him, and his wife conceiued: I doubt not but God had euer purpoſed, that at that verye moment, ſhee ſhoulde conceiue, yet to teach vs howe acceptable our praiers are vnto him, and how it pleaſeth him by the meanes therof to conuey our neceſſaries vnto vs, the text ſaith, <hi>The Lord was intreated of him, and Rebecka his wife con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen, 25.23</note> as though if <hi>Iſaac</hi> had not praied ſhe ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:21484:32"/>not haue conceiued, if you pleaſe to make vſe heereof, you may thus thinke that God for ought you know hath determined that your ſoule ſhall not become fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, nor conceiue and bring fourth this faith, vntill you beg the ſame of him by earneſt prayer, and that then, becauſe he is ſtill the ſame God he wil be intreated, and your ſoule ſhall be conceiued both of this faith and all other needeful graces that acompany the ſame to your eternall comfort.</p>
            <p>The other meanes to get faith is the hearing of Gods word, for faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God. The <hi>Samaritans</hi> vpon the report of a woman partly beleeued in chriſt, and thought that it might be hee whom they expected; but when they had heard him themſelues then they throughly belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and knew that he was that ſauiour which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. You haue beene tolde much of chriſt whoe is the foundation of faith by thoſe that haue conferred moſt with you about ſpirituall affaires, and ſomthing in this my letter you haue heard of him. But did you heare him your ſelfe ſpeake, I meane, did you read the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which are his owne wordes, and hard them read and expounded, by thoſe which are his faithfull mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; O then you would [I hope] not almoſt, but alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether become a chriſtian; then would you not partly but wholy beleeue in him that dyed for you; then wold your faith be no longer wauering, but throughly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed.</p>
            <p>For how could you chuſe but be ſtrengthned in your beliefe of him, when you ſhould be acquainted withall the things he did, and indured for your ſake? how could you chuſe but be rauiſhed in affection, and with the
<pb facs="tcp:21484:32"/>true church be ſicke of loue, when you ſhould heare him call you (notwithſtanding all your vnkind dealing towards him) <hi>his Siſter, his loue, his ſpouſe, his doue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Solo, ſong ch, 4, 9. ver 9.1.9, ch, 6, 8. ch, 6.8</note> 
               <hi>and his vndefiled.</hi> It maketh my heart bleede to thinke how you and many thouſands, [ſuch ſeely ſeduced inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents] are depriued of theſe, and infinite other ſuch like heauenly and vnexpreſſable conſolations. And all for the want of this worde of God, which you ſuffer to belocked vp from you, and wherewith [though it muſt import you] you are leaſt acquainted, chriſtes caueat ſhal be the concluſion of this point, <hi>He that hath eares to heare let him heare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly vnderſtand how cheape this faith will be vnto you. In a word, it will neither coſt you trauell nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, It will coſt you no trauell, for you neede but heare the voice of chriſt, when he cryeth vnto you, and open the doore of your heart vnto him when he knocketh thereupon by his word, and you ſhall receiue it,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.20</note> 
               <hi>behold</hi> [ſaith chriſt] <hi>I ſtand at the doore and knock, if any man heare my voice, and open the doore, I will come in vnto him and will ſup with him, and he with me:</hi> It will coſt you no money, for you neede but doe as the King of heauens proclamtion directeth you, and it ſhall be giuen you freely:<note place="margin">Eſai, 55.2</note> 
               <hi>Ho euery one</hi> [ſaith the prophet [<hi>that thirſteth come ye to the waters,</hi> (which are the ſacred ſcriptures, containing Gods reueiled counſell) <hi>and ye that haue no Siluer come buy and eate, come I ſay and buy wine and milke without ſiluer, and without mony;</hi> And theſe are nothing but faith, and the holy graces that acompany the ſame, which are as neceſſary, for the nouriſhment of the ſoule as Wine and Milke and ſuch like meate is, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the body.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21484:33"/>
            <p>THus, hauing [as I haue bin compelled] poaſted through theſe later parts;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Sect.</note> namely what the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine is that you muſt take, <hi>faith:</hi> the benifits you ſhall receiue thereby <hi>felicity in this world, and in the world to come:</hi> After what ſort you muſt get the ſame, <hi>By prayer and hearing Gods word:</hi> And laſtly, how little this ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Iewell will coſt you, <hi>Neither traueil nor money:</hi> &amp; being circulerly now returned to the word of god, theſe waters of comfort which at firſt be ſprinckled the front of my letter, let me intreat you, &amp; by no leſſe important regardes, then for the loue you beare to your owne ſoule, which muſt needes be deare vnto you, and for the loue and zeale you carrye to the glorye of God, which ſhould be dearer vnto you; that your euer ent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnclaſpe his holy booke, diligently peruſe the ſame, and daye and night euen continually, make the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes thereof, [with holy <hi>Dauid</hi>] your ſweete and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Meditation: if you wil not reade it at my requeſt, yet let me requeſt you to obſerue that wonderfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription wherby the Apoſtle, euen to inflame you with the loue thereof commendeth the ſame vnto you, <hi>The word of God</hi> [ſaith he] <hi>is liuely and mighty in operation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr, 4, 12</note> 
               <hi>and ſharper then any two edged ſword, and entreth through euen vnto the diuiding aſunder of the ſpirit and the iontes, and the marow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and the intents of the heart.</hi> To this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation of the apoſtle, I will adioyne the commaundement that God himſelfe giueth you touching the ſame,<note place="margin">Deut. xi, 18 19 20</note> in theſe very wordes, <hi>Therefore ye ſhall lay vp theſe my wordes in your heart, and in your ſoule, and bind them for a ſigne vpon your hand, that they may bee as a frontlet beeweene your eies, and
<pb facs="tcp:21484:33"/>you ſhall teach them your children, ſpeaking of them when thou ſitteſt in thine houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the waie, and when thou lieſt downe, and when thou riſeſt vp, and thou ſhalt write them vpon the poſtes of thine houſe, and vpon thy gates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the commaundement of Gods owne mouth vnto you; But alaſſe, how do you performe the ſame? How can you laye his wordes vp in your heart? How can you make ſuch a Iewell of them, when you neither reade them, nor heare them reade vnto you? Surely that is the cauſe of all, for as an ancient father ſaide of the <hi>Hereticks valentiniani,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ireneus cont, valen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tianos,</note> 
               <hi>that their ignorance in the Scriptures, had brought them to that paſſe.</hi> So queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe may I conclude, that your neglect of the worde which would be a Lanthorne vnto your feete and a light vnto your pathes, is the reaſon that you are thus miſſed in blindeneſſe, and ſo ſeduced with error and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And this your ghoſtly aduerſarie is well acquainted with, for he knowes that vnleſſe you reade or heare the word of God, you can neuer as the bleſſed mother of chriſt did, treaſure vp the ſame in your hart to your eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal inrich ment: he knoweth you can hardly beleeue a right with thoſe honeſt women of <hi>Boeriae</hi> vnleſſe as they did, you firſt receiue the word with readineſſe, whereby true reliefe is begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yea he knowes by his long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that where the word is not preached, the people for the moſt part periſh, and therfore where it is neither preached, nor reade, nor regarded, his kingdome muſt nedes floriſh, which maketh him ſo to beſtir him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by his vnhallowed miniſters amongſt you; ſo to diſcountnance the word vnto you and ſo with their falſe
<pb facs="tcp:21484:34"/>ſuggeſtions to diſcourage you from the reading of it, in calling it with their blaſphemous mouthes, imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, doubtfull, inſufficient, but a dead letter, and euen like a noſe of waxe, ſubiect to any impreſſion: and in telling you that by the reading thereof diuers haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Heretickes, howſoeuer, yet that it is impoſſible by ſuch as your ſelfe to be conceiued: But beleeue them not, no more then you would beleeue their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the father of lyes, euen falſhood it ſelfe if you ſaw it vnmasked: For you may be aſſured that the word of God is perfect, pure, &amp; vndefiled, and that albeit ſome places in the ſcripturs be obſcure, yet [generally] they giue vnderſtanding to the ſimple, and are [as <hi>Iraeneus</hi> ſaith] <hi>Plaine without doubtfulneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iraeneus lib. 1. cap, 31 Gregorius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>epiſt, id Leand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
               <hi>and may be heard in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently of all men.</hi> Therein is milke and proper nutriment, euen for the tendreſt babe that euer lay in the lap of the church, <hi>It is a water</hi> [ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>] <hi>wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the little lambe</hi> [ſuch as your ſelfe] <hi>may wade, and the mighty Elephant</hi> [meaning the learned ones] <hi>may ſwim,</hi> which Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> likewiſe affirmed, ſaying that <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God in the ſcriptures ſpeaketh as a familiar friende without diſsimulation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtine Epiſt 3. ad Voluſianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> not to the learned only, <hi>but both to the learned and vnlearned.</hi> And with theſe holy fathers of the church, the reſt generally accorde herein, inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by their ſtrongeſt perſwaſions, all ſorts of people, the ignorant with the wiſe, the learned and vnlearned, together to repaire hether for their inſtruction, and from hence, as touching the diſcharge of their chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Office, both towardes God and manto fetch theyr abſolute direction. This may giue you occaſion to woonder what your Prieſtes meane ſo perimptorily to interdict you the vſe of the holy ſcriptures, when the
<pb facs="tcp:21484:34"/>learned Fathers, [whom notwithſtanding they will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently challenge to be wholly theirs,] were neuer heard in that tune, but euer taught the contrary: the reaſon heereof is eaſily gathered, they know that the worde of God being abſolutely trueth, muſt needes, were you acquainted with it, diſcouer their falſhoode vnto you. They knowe that the nature of it being to giue light, it would quickly expell that <hi>Caemerian darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> wherewith your ſence is ſo inveloped, and by meanes whereof they lead you blindfolded into their denne of I dolatrie, and abhomination at their pleaſure, they know that then you woulde ſoone perceiue their Iuggling, and that thereby you would plainly diſcerne them in their propper colours: Let them pretende therefore what they will, but this chiefely is the cauſe,<note place="margin">Tertullian in libro, de Trinit. chriſoſtom in opere imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, Ho, 14</note> for as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith. <hi>The ſacred ſcriptures doe conuince and diſcouer the guiles of Haeretickes,</hi> which <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> likewiſe obſerued when he ſaide, <hi>Hereticke prieſtes ſhut faſt the gates of the truth,</hi> meaning they conceale the worde of God from the people: <hi>Becauſe they knowe that if the trueth appeare, they muſt of neceſsity forſake their church,</hi> I aduiſe therefore to forſake their Counſell herein, and will propoſe vnto you, for an excellent pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of imitation, thoſe godly Siſters in chriſt which accompanied that Religious Paule at <hi>Bethlem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hierom in Epitaph, Paulae</note> who by the teſtimony of <hi>Hierome,</hi> accounted it vnlawfull to to be ignorant in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and ſpent not one day without learning ſomething out of the Scriptures. And that vertuous <hi>Gorgonia;</hi> whome her brother the good <hi>Nazianze</hi> in his Funerall oration ouer her, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for being expert both in the olde and new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let theſe holy virgins, and bleſſed handmaids of
<pb facs="tcp:21484:35"/>Chriſt be your preſident, go hand in hand with them, as will beſt become you, and moſt redound to your aduantage, vnto this ſacred Fountaine of Gods word, this holy well indeed, inſteed of your extraordinarie vnſanctified Sai. <hi>Winifreds:</hi> For hereof you may drink your ſill, and haue your thirſt quenched, heerewith you may waſh your ſelfe, and haue your leproſie clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, herin your ſoul [for that is the proper vertue of it] may find an heauenly ſolace, and be conuerted. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake I ſay their doctrine, herein, Nay forſake and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon both the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; their doctrin, them as no miniſters of chriſt, their doctrine as meere <hi>Antichriſtian:</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Miniſters of chriſt deliuer with Paule no other do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſaue that which they haue receiued of chriſt: but they teach you the quite contrary, as in forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you to read the ſcriptures, when chriſt commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth you to reade them. <hi>Search the ſcriptures</hi> ſayeth chriſt,<note place="margin">Io. 5, 3, 9</note> ſerch them not ſay they. They tel you that the reading of them would driue you into errour:<note place="margin">Mar. xii. 29</note> But chriſt telleth you, that your error groweth becauſe you read them not. Is not heere a plain oppoſition betwixt chriſt and them, his doctrine and theirs? What recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning then ſhould you make of them: The Apoſtle tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you, that if a very Angell ſhould come from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and preach vnto you ſuch doctrin as this, ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from that which he and the other apoſtles haue preached, you ſhould be ſo far from beleeuing him, as rather to hold him accurſed.</p>
            <p>Surely theſe fellows are ſuch, as our carefull and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſhephearde giueth vs that friendly caueat to take heed of.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, 7.15, 16</note> 
               <hi>Beware</hi> [ſaith he] <hi>of falſe prophets, which come to you in ſheepes cloathing,</hi> [vnder the colour of holines and
<pb facs="tcp:21484:35"/>innocency, but this is the outward man onely, <hi>For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly they are rauening Wolues.</hi> And the means wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may diſtinguiſh them from the true Miniſters of chriſt is this: <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits.</hi> And here I might take occaſion, to giue you a further taſt of the fruits of your religion, namely of the doctrine, and conuerſation which your <hi>Popes, cardinals, Priests, Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its,</hi> and others generally of your church, from theyr inſtruction and tolleration, haue taught and practiſed, wherby after the rule of our ſauiour in knowing the tree by the fruit, you might the more plainly perceine your church, which you are ſo confidently perſwaded, is the true church of chriſt, to be no other then the very Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue of Satan. But it is too ſpatious a field for mee to pace through, it were the taske rather of a mans life, a ſubiect for a mighty volume. To omit therefore their doctrine and life in generall, I will lay before you one onely inſtaunce hereof, which by the argument of our Sauiour, being fruit ſo rotten and ilſauery, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, [you may be aſſured] ſpring from a roote as bitter and corrupted.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Obſeruations vpon the late diſcouered Treaſons.</head>
               <p>AND I will not looke backe to former times,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>7.</hi> Sect.</note> nor trauell forreine countries for the accident, It is that hotrible and inhuman conſpiracy, bred and foſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the boſome of your religion, and of late by the prouidence &amp; ſweet mercy of our god, ſo bleſſedly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered and defeated. A conſpiracy againſt the ſayreſt, againſt the Lord, and againſt his anoynted. And may I not ſay againſt all the ſoules of Iſraell, that bare true
<pb facs="tcp:21484:36"/>faith, and true allegiance to God and their ſoueraigne? For all them, ſhould haue felt the force of that terrible blow, that was threatned, and in ſome degree or other pertaked of the <hi>Tragedy,</hi> A <hi>Tregedy</hi> whereunto althe <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies</hi> of the world, begin with that of <hi>Abell,</hi> and come along all ages, to the laſt that dranke of that cup in our owne memory would haue giuen place, and for horror, monſtroſiſme, and true eſſentiall diueliſhneſſe, could not haue bin compared. Which would haue made all the bloody villaines, that euer breathed, better, or at leaſt leſſe thought vpon, becauſe the cogitations of all the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſe parts of the earth wold only haue bin caſt therupon, as they are partly already but with the ſame of the intention: No, the like Tragedy was neuer acted, nor [I thinke] by the moſt abſolute incarnate Diuell e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer before plotted, A plot [as <hi>Lauid</hi>] ſpeaketh, to haue rooted vs out ſo many thouſads, yea millions within this kingdome, that we ſhould haue been no more a people, and that the very name of a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> [vnleſſe in by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word] ſhould haue beene no more in remembrance, as [indeede] had they [acording as they proiected] made that hauock of them altogether, his ſacred Maieſty, our gratious Queene, the hopefull <hi>Prince,</hi> and all thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and worthy ones, their attendants, it had not beene altogether improbable.</p>
               <p>But this while you will ſay I proue not [as I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke] that this conſpiracy, which moſt of you, (with your tongues at leaſt) wil confeſſe, was wicked, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtifiable, to be the fruites of your religion, or any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of your life and doctrine: for the cleering wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of can I deale more plainely, then out of your owne mouth as it were to iudge you, or produce better
<pb facs="tcp:21484:36"/>proofes then the poſitions and concluſions of your owne clerks, and greateſt diuines approuing and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, that in ſome caſes it is lawfull for ſubiects, to riſe vp in arme, againſt their King, and that the depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of an <hi>Heretick</hi> prince ſuch as they take our King to be is a commendable worke and meritorious.</p>
               <p>Vnderſtand therefore that <hi>Allen, Baines, Saunders, Parſons, creſwell, Reynoles, Tollet, Tellarmine,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers on whoſe ſhoulders as vpon ſo many arch-pillers your church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath for this many yeares beene ſupported haue taught and publiſhed the ſaid doctrin, as appeareth in their ſeuerall writings, wherof ſome few are collected in this booke intituled, <hi>An exact, diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of romiſh doctrine in caſe of conſpiraſie and rebellion by pregnant obſeruations,</hi> which heerewith I haue ſent you, or purpoſe to giue you a better view of their horrible doctrine not heerein onely but touching other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters likewiſe which may inſtly occaſion you to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them, and deteſt their courſes for euer: and that this conſpiracy may be taken as an inſtance of their life likewiſe, who can make doubt, when they themſelues ſhould haue beene the performers thereof, when the plotters, actors, abetrers, and all that ſhould haue waſhed their handes in that bloody baſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, were <hi>Papiſts,</hi> deuoted to your church, and ſuch as you call Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes. It is therefore [queſtionleſſe] an inſtance of their life and doctrine the proper fruites of their Religion: yea, yea, it is a babe of their owne begetting euery ynch of it: And though they ſearch each corner of their wit to ſhift it off and father it vpon others, yet ſhal it alwaies be reputed theirs, They ſhall euer bee infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to keepe it, and be are it vpon their backs as a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="tcp:21484:37"/>badge of their fornication, and a durable monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their ſhame, whiles the world indureth: yet is it worthy obſeruation, to note what poore deuiſes they haue, and what iniſerable ſhiftes they are driuen vnto, I meane your <hi>Prieſtes</hi> and <hi>Iheſuites</hi> and ſuch as you moſt depend vpon, and are chiefely directed by, to daube vp the matter [if they could] at leaſt to preſerue their eſtimation awhile amongſt you, and (though it lye a dying) to lynger it out as long as is poſſible. But to omit the reſt, I will onely mention that which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth their finall refuge, and ſerueth them for the beſt ſhelter to beare of the force off this imputation. They maintaine, that although the conſpirators were all of them profeſſed to the Church of Rome, yet that it was not the doctrine of that church, but ambition, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment, and deſperate eſtate, that drew them thereunto; for their doctrine gaue warrant for no ſuch courſes, and that without queſtion the Popes holineſſe could neuer be touched therewith. To the former pointe I haue already anſwered, and proued vnto you by the Teſtimony of their moſt famous and profoundeſt diuines, that it is the doctrine of their church, and therefore by all likelyhood they receiued their protection thence, and it was that, which gaue them their chiefe encouragment. Now whether the Pope [whom you call the head of your church] were priuy to the damnable purpoſe of theſe all-bloody mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreants, this worſe then <hi>Catilniary</hi> crew of conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, whom it cannot be denyed were members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I know not; howbeit, the regard of ſimpathy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the head and the members, together with conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
<pb facs="tcp:21484:37"/>that the greateſt part of the prize in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood would haue fallen to his ſhare, may ſeeme a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall ground for a ſuſpition: But this I dare ſaie, that if he were not acquainted with the plot, nor would haue aplauded it, if he had beene; but beareth a minde oppoſite to ſuch deſeignes, he is an honeſter man then ſome of his predeceſſors haue beene. Witneſſe the letter which <hi>N.</hi> the <hi>Cardinall</hi> of <hi>Como</hi> ſent vnto <hi>Parry,</hi> for the murthering of our deere deceaſed Soueraigne of famous memory, <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> to this effect.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>SYr the Popes holines hath peruſed your letter, and cannot but commend your good diſpoſition, &amp; reſolution, which (as you ſay) tendeth to the publike benefit; wherein his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe exhorteth you to perſist, and to effect that which you promiſe. And becauſe you may be the better aſsisted by that good ſpirit which hath induced you to this, his bleſſedneſſe graunteth you full pardon and forgiueneſſe of all your ſinnes as you deſired; aſſuring you, that beſides the merit which you receiue in heauen, his holineſſe will become a further debtor to acknowledge your deſeruings in the beſt ſort hee may. And the rather for that you vſe ſo great modeſty in pretending nothing. Put therefore in execution your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and holy thoughtes, and looke to your ſafety. And ſo I preſent my ſelfe hartely vnto you, and wiſh you all good and happy ſucceſſe: From Rome the thirty of Ianuary <hi>1584.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Yours to diſpoſe</hi> N. Cardinall of Como.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb facs="tcp:21484:38"/>
               <p>If this letter will not fatiſie you, that your Popes haue approued ſuch bloody courſes, take notice I pray you how <hi>Pope Gregory</hi> the ninth made a decree,<note place="margin">Decretum Greg. 9 cauſe. 23</note> that anye man might renounce, and imbrewe his handes in the bloud of his kinſinan, his ſonne, his father, or whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer without deſtinction, in caſe he were an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, [as al were adiudged that profeſſed not papiſtry.] And how <hi>Pope Sextus quintus,</hi> tooke vpon him the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of an orator, and in a publicke and premeditated ſpeech before all his cardinals, extolled to the skies, that Wicked <hi>Monke,</hi> which ſo murthered <hi>Henry</hi> the third, King of <hi>France,</hi> commending the murther for a notable, rare, and merueilous peece of worke, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the murthered, as an vnfortunate king dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his ſinne, and beſtowing no worſe a title then <hi>Religious man,</hi> vpon the villaine that was the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. And laſtly,<note place="margin">Bulla <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> how <hi>Pope Pius quintus</hi> practiſed the death of our ſaide <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> ánd ſent his Bull for that purpoſe, importing as followeth: <hi>It is our will and we comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>und; that the ſubiects of England take them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to armes againſt Elizabeth their Queene.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe few mirrors, the eye that is not vtterly blind may plainely diſcerne, whether your Popes be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact of nothinge but fanctety, and integrity, as they are continually deſcribed vnto you, and howe their harts cleaning faſt to the former grounds, reſt affected in ſuch a caſe of murthering princes, and incitinge their ſubiects to rebellion: This ſeemeth then a weake ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er but ſhame muſt haue a couer, though it be but of fig leaues.</p>
               <p>I could [methinkes] out of the bowels of chriſtian charity, from my hart deplore, that they who profeſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21484:38"/>the true ſeruice of God, and in ſome ſort call vppon the name of Ieſus, ſhould ſo far degenerate from the nature of a chriſtian, as to plot, and proſequte to the period, ſuch a monſtrous and diuelliſh deſeign, as the hart of the moſt irreligious, and hardeſt-frozen Atheiſt would haue trembled at, and the worſt of thoſe barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Seythian</hi> bloud-ſuckers, could not but haue abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Which the idolatrous Turke, and all wicked <hi>Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks</hi> will for euer [I think] as an argument againſt the pretious bloude of our fauiour, caſt into the teeth of Chriſtendome, becauſe it putteth down call the world for a point of immanity, irreligion, and compleat vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany. <hi>Inquire</hi> [ſaid <hi>Moſes</hi>] <hi>of the antiant daies, which are before thee, ſince the day that God created man vppon the earth, and from one end of heauen to the other, if euer there were the like thing done.</hi> And is not this ſpeech, [though fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a different ground] proper to this conſpiracy, if the laſt worde be left out? Indeede, it was not abſolutely done, for the bow brake at the vp hot, It was done to theſe your catholicks, that wiſhed and went about the doing of it. We giue them like thankes, and GOD <hi>[without Repentance]</hi> will giue them the like reward, as if it had bene done. But it was not done to our Kinge, to our Queene, to our Prince, and thoſe thouſandes, which by the power of that infernall blaſt, ſhoulde no doubt haue accompanied them to the preſence of the eternall Maieſty: It was not done vnto them, bleſſed be our mercifull God, that vndid it, and out of his all-louing kindnes to his church, ſo gratiouſly put his owne right hande, which bringeth mighty [things to paſſe, betwixte the purpoſe and the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb facs="tcp:21484:39"/>Surely, they thought themſelues of gods priuy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell:<note place="margin">In the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the lord Moun togle.</note> 
                  <hi>God and man haue concurred to puniſh the wickednes of the time:</hi> But had they bin ſo much as of his court, they would better haue known his pleaſure, for there they would haue herd the Lord, giuing them this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> There <hi>Dauid</hi> would haue asked them this queſtion: <hi>Who can lay hand on the Lord annotn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and be guiltleſſe:</hi> There Paule would haue ſet them downe this poſition, <hi>Whoſoeuer reſiſt, purchaſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues damnation.</hi> The Tyrauntes boaſted that they could do miſchiefe,<note place="margin">In the ſaid Letter to the Lord Mo.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſay they ſhal receiue a terrible blow,</hi> but we felt that <hi>the goodneſſe of God ſtill indured.</hi> The Lord, (according to the prayer of <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>woulde not deliuer the ſoules of ſo many of his Turtle Doues vnto the multitude of their enemies, and therefore he ſhot at them with a ſwift aroow, &amp; hewed the ſnares of theſe vngodlie ones in pecces:</hi> yet in ſomthing they ſaid truth, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of that confident menace fell out right: <hi>And yet they ſhal not ſee who hurt them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In the ſaid Letter</note> They do not [indeed] God that ſhielded them from that terrible blow, be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer praiſed.</p>
               <p>They do not ſee who hurt them, but they ſee that which thoſe vipers little thought they ſhoulde haue ſeene; they ſee ſome of thoſe that woulde haue hurt them, and [I hope] will ſee the reſt, howſoeuer I knowe they are ſeene, and will be remembred ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to his bleſſed will, that beſt knoweth how to rewarde them. They doe not ſee who hurte them, but they ſee who preſerued them from hurt.</p>
               <p>His Maieſty doeth ſee, and acknowledge, that it
<pb facs="tcp:21484:39"/>was the ſame God that ſtoode ſo neere his holy father King <hi>Dauid</hi> in al his daungers, <hi>That ſaued his life ſo oft from deſtruction, and crowned him with ſuch mercy and louing kindneſſe:</hi> that it was the ſame God that ſtucke as cloſe to his deare Siſter Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in all her troubles, and from her cradle, till he had ſet the crown vpon hir head, &amp; during al the time of hir moſt famous and victorious raigne, preſerued her as the Apple of his eie, and neuer left her, vntill he had chaunged her corruptible crowne of golde, to an incorruptible crowne of glory, for her greater aduancemenr: and finally, that it was the ſame God, which had couered him likewiſe from time to time, vnder his gratious wings, and made him taſte [ere that day] the ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his mercye, as ſencibly as <hi>Dauid,</hi> or <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> or any other of thoſe deare annointed ones, had done before him: yea that preuented him with his liberall bleſſinges, and protected him, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the houre of his byrth, [ſince the worlde inioyed him,] but which is more woonderfull, whiles the happie wombe of his Mother incloſed him: <hi>Many a time haue they vexed me from my youth, vp,</hi> may our king ſay with <hi>Iſraell, but they haue not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed againſt me.</hi> And I will ſay with thoſe of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> that pray for the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and wiſh well to <hi>Syon,</hi> I hope they neuer ſhall: for I doubt not, but God hath euer ſworne by his holineſſe, as he did to king Dauid, and <hi>queene Elizabeth,</hi> that he will neuer faile king <hi>Iames.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With the like eie of thankfulnes, doth the <hi>queen,</hi> the <hi>Prince,</hi> the <hi>peeres,</hi> and all the reſt looke vppon their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery: acknowledging God only to be their deliuerer:
<pb facs="tcp:21484:40"/>yea the graue <hi>Neſiors</hi> themſelues, whoſe wiſe dome may be termed a brazen wail to our kingdome, doe ſee that a deeper reach, and far greater prouidence then theirs, euen the wiſedome of the almighty was the principall worker heerein: and therefore, [for all their paynes, and prudence in the diſcouery] lay the matter wholy from themſelues, and ſtill make this their concluſion: <hi>Not vnto vs Lord, not vnto vs, but vnto thy name giue the praiſe.</hi> And all, from the greateſt to the meaneſt, that ſhould inſtantly, or by degrees, haue taſted of the ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem, doe ſee [likewiſe] not who hurt them: but who preſerued them: and accord in this ioyfull acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>It was thy hand O Lord that did it:</hi> I wonder what conſtruction the fauourers of your profeſſion make of the accident. I know how they carry it outwardly, but what their inward man thinketh of it, in approbation or deteſtatation of the plot, and touching the diſcouery, theres the point. One of the principals ſeemed onely ſorry that the matter tooke not effect, and ſlood to it (like himſelfe) that it was not God it was the Dyuell that preuented it: But the deſperate, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> miſcreant, that inchriſtian &amp; vncircumciſed Philiſtine, with all of that opinion, were vtterly deceiued, for the dyuell
[without queſtion] would haue ſung <hi>Gaudeamus</hi> with the merieſt. that day would in all likelihood] haue beene the Dyuels holiday: and therefore, in deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight of him, but chiefely to render vnto our gratious God from whom our ſaluation commeth, the ſacrifice of praiſe and thankſgiuing, the very ſame daic ſhall for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be our holiday.</p>
               <p>But to leaue them that draw ſuch euill vſe from this, as generally they doe from all other occurrents, in the
<pb facs="tcp:21484:40"/>preiudice of their miſconſtruction: It is the deſire of my heart, and would be a ioy vnto my ſoule, that you [for your part) would make a profitable vſe therof, that with the true ſeruantes of God, you would draw good out of this euill, meditate thereupon, and ſeriouſly ponder each circumſtance belonging therunto, which would [I make no queſtion] proue a happy meanes to remoue you out of the baſe and erronious ſchoole, that readeth whole lectures of ignorance vnto you, and wherein ouerlong you haue beene trayned vp, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nothing but abſurdities, vnto that beſt learned, and moſt Godly vniuerſity, which will in rich your hart with diuiue wiſedome; and wherein to your great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and vnſpeakable benifit you ſhall be tutord, and conſorted with true chriſtians.</p>
               <p>And to this end, I mean for your learning this one leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of making the right vſe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracy, which may ſo much auaile you, diſdaine me not (how vnworthy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer I ſeeme) the place of your ſcholemaiſter. Thus then (I pray you) learne to read after me. Surely, it was the mighty hand of God, that defeated the purpoſe of thoſe blood-thirſty papiſts, thoſe more then barbarous conſpirators: It was his tender mercy that ſet his hand, to that happy and euer memorable piece of worke; they were his beloued ſeruants vnto whom ſuch mercy was extended, that is his true church, wherof thoſe his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes are members, and therefore by neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that is plainely oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to this church of God, that is in deadly enmity with theſe ſeruantes of God, that inwardly repineth at this mercy of God and that is ſo manifeſtly oppugned by this hande of God, is the falſe church, no church of
<pb facs="tcp:21484:41"/>chriſt but the very idolatious and abhominable Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Antichriſt. This is but a ſhort eſſon: howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it if you con the ſame perfectly l y hart, and truely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, you ſhall feele your ſoule [I doubt not] ſo ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon the deepe conſideration of this ſauing hand, ſo wrapt vp with the ſweet admiration of this exceeding mercy, ſo inflamed with the burning deſire to be ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cked amongſt theſe happy ſeruants, ſo rauiſhed with the zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus loue of this church, that you wil reſt aſſured &amp; moſt reſolutely conclude, that we whom the Lord in ſuch gratious ſort preſerueth vnder the ſhadow of his wings, who are ſo deere and tender vnto him, and whom hee thus hedgeth about, and hemmeth in on euery ſide, are his peculiar people, his choſen generation, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his true church, and that your church of Rome [which indeed as the prophet ſpeaketh of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi>] was [in the primitiue time] <hi>A righteous citty and full of equity, is become vnfaithfull as a whore, though righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe did dewell in it, yet, that now it is inhabited with murtherers, and that her ſiluer is turned to droſſe, and her wine is mixt with water.</hi> Thus [I ſay] if you make true vſe of this conſpiracy [queſtionleſſe] you wil conclude, and concluding ſo, for ſake <hi>Bahilon</hi> and enter into <hi>Zion,</hi> and for the good eſtate of your ſoule, moſt willingly embrace this counſel of your Lord, and ſauiour. <hi>Come away from her my people that you be not partakers of her ſinnes and that you receiue not of her plagues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now giue me leaue in a worde to knit vp this point of treaſon, for which the <hi>Iheſuites,</hi> the ſecular prieſts and their followers (miſtiled catholickes) are become ſo egregious, with the chriſtian and vntainted reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the profeſſors of our religion touching ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeignes.
<pb facs="tcp:21484:41"/>I, that prize my ſelfe as the leaſt of Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and challenge no prerogatiue of ſaithfulneſſe to my King and countrey, aboue the loyalty of an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proteſtant, do
[without any of thoſe mentall irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious referuations] ſolemnely proteſt, that were I ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by an Angell from he men, to poſſeſſe as much wealth, and attaine vnto aſmuch wiſedome as <hi>Salomon</hi> did, to ſway as many kingdomes as <hi>Aſuerus</hi> did, to liue as faire an age as <hi>Methuſelah</hi> did, and in fine, to take my leaue of the world, with an eaſie, and quiet diſſolution: yet would I not, in liea of all this earthly bleſſedneſſe, once lift vp my hand, or ſo much as incline my heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the depoſing of my lawful ſoueraigne the Lords anointed, no not although my king were a tyrant, as we all know, and his very enemies acknowledge he is grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and mild, and [after the Apoſtles precept] <hi>hath put on euen the howels of compaſsion;</hi> but concerning this laſt treaſon, that treaſon of treaſons, the vnparalleld arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaſon of the world, my proteſtation ſhall extend it ſelfe fvrther: Namely, that were I aſſared [beſides the fruition of all the former cited felicity] that my God neither in this world by the worme of conſcience, nor in the world to come by eternall confuſion, would lay the ſame to my charge but abſolutly remit it for euer, yet, that I ſhould abhor from my ſoule ſuch a bloody &amp; inhumaine action, &amp; neuer be won to giue my conſent thereunto, for my loue to god and his church, my king, and country, would [I know] religiouſly, and forcibly reſtrain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne; heere you may thinke I go very far, but I aſſure you no fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her then I am directed by holy war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; and this, I affirme to be the true reſolution of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant and preſent vnto you as the proper fruit of our religion.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21484:42"/>
               <p>Whereupon if you pleaſe to fix the eie of your ſoule, which is your vnderſtanding, and weigh the ſame in the true and ſingle ballance of impartial Iudgment, you wil preſently [I doubt not] diſtaſt the fruits of your religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and happely diſcouer the ſame, not to be as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, but rather like the aples of <hi>Sodome,</hi> which are ſaid to be faire and beautifull in ſhew, but when they are touched, turne to aſhes, and reueile themſelues to be of no ſubſtance: But I ouerlong detaine you, and confeſſe it is more then hie time I had concluded: I leaue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this, and all the other pointes formerly touched, to your mature and indifferent conſideration, and theirs [whomſoeuer] that ſhall likewiſe daigne the peruſall thereof, and will now make bold, (though an vnbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den gueſt, and but an intruder) to come to your wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>It ſhould ſeem [without impeachment of the gent. worth] that the deere expence of your time, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and vnualuable Iewell, was an eloquent and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull aduocate in his behalf, that at laſt hath ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily made conqueſt of your affection: wherein I muſt approue your wiſedome, for there is no earthly Iewel to be compared therewith. Iewels being loſt, may by poſſibility be recouered againe, but time being ſpent can neuer be recalled againe. I condemne my ſelfe in iuſtiſieng of you. Indeede therein (I confeſſe) I haue bene a prodigall, for I haue played ſo long at this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous game of delay, that I deſerue methinkes to be notorious for ill husbandry. The idle time-ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der being [as it is truely ſaide] the greateſt vnthrift: you haue conſide ratiuely avoided this ſcandall, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I onely ſay this; that as you haue bin wiſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:21484:42"/>into that happy and honourable calling of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and for ought I knowe, aduiſed in making your choiſe; ſo it is and ſhall be my prayer, how weake ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you account the power thereof, that you may bee hleſſed in your courſe, that your husbande that lyeth in your boſom, the yſſue which is likely to ſpring from thoſe imbracements, and all other bleſſings belonging to marriage, may deriue vnto you ſuch contentment ment and happineſſe, as your vttermoſt deſires can aime at, or any Gentlewoman of the world euer inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If you haue deſerued well of me, this [for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent] is my beſt requitall, if otherwiſe, it is my vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt reuenge.</p>
               <p>But if the world (which is wedded to idle inquiſition) and ſicke of her old diſeaſe, (ſiniſter miſconſtruction) would vnderſtand the reaſon that brake the marriage betwixt vs two, and gaue you occaſion otherwiſe to diſpoſe of yourſelfe, as you haue done: let them know, that [on my part] nothing but our different religion was the impediment, I appeale vnto yourſelfe whether I ſpeake truely: For you cannot but remember that in all oportunity, I was ſtill harping vpon that ſtring, and euer did my beſt (though all in vaine) to haue ſet the ſame in perfect tune. I told you, that if you would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your groſſe and fooliſh opinions, or but giue mee hope that in future time, I ſhould haue better hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and might happily win you thereunto, I woulde be moſt willing, and thinke my ſelfe moſt happy to knit that gordean knot, without longer deferring; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our friends ſhould vtterly withſtand it, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen inforce vs to get our maintenance: I, with my pen, and you with your needle, yea albeit we were ſure to
<pb facs="tcp:21484:43"/>haue gone a begging, which we then had not, neither I hope euer that haue reaſon to ſtand in feare of: Theſe words I ſpake oftner then once vnto you, I ſpake them from my hart, I proteſted that I ſpake them ſo, and I proteſt againe that I proteſted truly: This
[methinks] may diſcharge me from all imputations touching that matter, and vpon this targe of proofe will I ſafely take all the malevolent darts, that ſhall be throwne againſt my reputation; I ſay, if I was not ſo forward, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as the world expected, and your worth required, our different manner of doing God ſeruice gaue the occaſion: And you are not the only Iewell of worth, for I will euer acknowledge your worth, your morral ver. tues, your gifts of natur, all your praiſe-worthy parts, as al are praiſe-worthy, that, that onely, which (obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ali the reſt,) excepted: I ſay you are not the onely Iewell of worth, that this religious, and lawfull impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment hath debarred me the wearing of: But my god whoſe bleſſed will I refer my ſelf vnto, and vpon whoſe holy pronidence, I pray I may euer depende, will [I know] ſufficiently prouide for thoſe that faithfuly truſt in his goodneſſe, and in his inſinite and vnſpeakeable diſtribution of bleſſings. [I am in good hope] not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get my poor and ſinful ſelfe though his moſt vnworthy ſeruant.</p>
               <p>And ſo I beſeech his diuine Maieſty <hi>Our almightie creator,</hi> for the merit of his deere ſonne <hi>Our merciful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer</hi> by the illumination of his bleſſed ſpirit, <hi>Our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſancliſier to renew you in the ſpirit of your mind:</hi> to giue you grace to <hi>lay lowne the old man which is corrupt, and to put on that new man, which [after God] is ſhapen in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and holineſſe of truth: To ſill you with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:21484:43"/>of his will, in all wiſedome and ſpirituall vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to free you from theſe ſtrong deluſions,</hi> and to giue you, a true, liuely, &amp; iuſtifieng faith in the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Chriſt Ieſus our Sauior, wherby you haue cauſe to ſay and ſing with holy <hi>Dauid, My ſoul is eſcaped euen as a bird out of the ſnare of the fowler, the ſnare is broken, and I am deliuered. That when your houſe of clay, whoſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is but duſt, ſhall be conſumed. You may be tranſlated into the great citty holy Ieruſalem, be fed by the Lambe, which is in the midſt of the throne, be led into the fountains of liuing water, haue all your teares wiped from your eyes:</hi> And in a word be crowned amongſt the true ſeruants of the euerliuing God with eternall ioy and felicity in heauen: where I hope, notwithſtanding our ſeperation vppon carth, we ſhall one day by the mercy of our god, liue and raign together.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:21484:44"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:21484:44"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
